<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Two common places taken out of Andreas Hyperius, a learned diuine, whereof, in the one, he sheweth the force that the sonne, moone and starres haue ouer men, &amp;c. In the other, whether the deuils haue bene the shewers of magicall artes, &amp;c. Translated into English by R.V.</title>
            <author>Hyperius, Andreas, 1511-1564.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1581</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 110 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 63 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A01631</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 11762</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S105728</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99841454</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99841454</idno>
            <idno type="VID">6039</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A01631)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6039)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 384:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Two common places taken out of Andreas Hyperius, a learned diuine, whereof, in the one, he sheweth the force that the sonne, moone and starres haue ouer men, &amp;c. In the other, whether the deuils haue bene the shewers of magicall artes, &amp;c. Translated into English by R.V.</title>
                  <author>Hyperius, Andreas, 1511-1564.</author>
                  <author>Vaux, Robert.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>79, 40-55, 78-110 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted by Iohn Wolfe,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1581.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Sources of texts not traced.</note>
                  <note>Translator's dedication signed: R. Vaux.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Astrology --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Demonology --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Magic --  Religious aspects --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:6039:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6039:1"/>
            <p>TWO COMMON PLACES TAKEN OVT OF ANDREAS HYPERIVS A LEARNED diuine, whereof,</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>In the one, He ſheweth the force that the Sonne, Moone and Starres haue ouer men, &amp;c.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>In the other, Whether the Deuils haue bene the ſhewers of Magicall artes, &amp;c.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Tranſlated into Engliſh by R. Y.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>VBIQVE FLORESCIT.</p>
            </figure>
            <p>LONDON Imprinted by Iohn Wolfe 1581.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:6039:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:6039:2"/>
            <head>To the worſhipfull and his eſpeciall good frend M. Latham of Sandowne in Eſſex.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Our very courteous af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fabilitie, whereof I haue had ſo great experience, continuing without any ſhew of a mutable mind hath greatelye moued myne affection to make no ſmall account of your worſhips frend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip. And I would to God that it were in me by any meanes to make any ſmall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendes vnto you for the ſame. Which to do is eaſier for me to wiſh than to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhe. Wherefore as there is no remedie but that I muſt remayne endebted: ſo on the contrary parte to ſhew no ſignes of a willing minde, were nothing els but a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt toke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of an ingrateful perſon. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon hauing peruſed certaine of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon places contained in the Methode of <hi>Hyperius</hi> and lighting vpon theſe two here ſpecified, and thinking them not vnmeete
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:6039:3"/>to be reuealed for the inſtruction of the people: I purpoſed for declaration of my louing mind toward you to put them forth in print dedicated vnto your worſhip. Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to whome I know they ſhall be no leſſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable then if they were thinges of very great account. Thus committing you and your affaires to the protection of the hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gheſt; I bid you farewell.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours to commaund R. Vaux.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:6039:3"/>
            <head>An admonition to the Reader.</head>
            <p>THou art to conſider gentle Reader that a tranſlator is bounde as nighe as may be vnto his author that he pretendeth to tranſlate, ſo that he is not onelye to ſhewe his ſenſe and meaninge: but as farre forth as may be to ſhew his very wordes. Wherefore if in tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninge ſome places of the holy ſcripture by mine au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor cited, I do not aunſweare thine expectation: thou maiſt, ſeing thou haſt thoſe places quoted vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee, haue recourſe if it pleaſe thee to thine owne tranſlation, which peraduenture is plainelier done to thy capacitie, and becauſe thou art accuſtomed thereunto, more to thy contentation. And ſo yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge to <hi>Hyperius</hi> the prayſe which he hath well deſerued for his labors: thou mayſt contente thy minde.</p>
            <p>Farewell.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="excerpt">
            <pb facs="tcp:6039:4"/>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:6039:4"/>
            <head>THE FOVRTH DAY WORKE BY GOD MENTIONED GE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſis the firſt chapter.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Oyſes proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge the great workes of God, writeth that in the fourth daye were made ligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes in the firma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of heauen, which myght geue lyght to the earth, might make diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betwene daye and nyght, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene lyght and darknes, and myght be for ſignes and for tymes, and for dayes, and for yeares. There were two ſuch lightes made, the one grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to gouerne the day, the other leſſe to gouerne the night: to the which alſo are adioyned the ſtarres. Theſe queſtions therfore in this place are to be diſcourſed.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1 What are the offices of the Sonne and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:6039:5"/>Mone, and how they be for ſignes and tymes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2 Whether there be diſtincte circles in heauen, and the ſame be driuen about with a ſure &amp; certen motion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3 Whether by the mouing of the circles, there be any concent or harmonie brought forth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4 Whether the Starres haue lyfe,<note place="margin">&amp; 44.</note> as they thoughte which did offer drinke offeringes to the Quene of heauen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">
               <hi>5 Whether the Starres and the celeſtiall mouinges do bringe to paſſe any thinge vpon theſe inferior bodies</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As touchinge the firſte queſtion,<note place="margin">firſt ſtion.</note> The lighte was made the firſte daye. There was alſo a difference betwene lighte and darknes: but certayne it is, that it was not ſo perfecte and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed, as it was after the Son and Moone were made: beſyde that thoſe effectes coulde not come of that lighte which afterwarde folowed of the Sonne and the Moone. It ſhall therfore be worth the while, to waigh the offices ot the Sonne and Moone
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:6039:5"/>whereby wee ſhall vnderſtande, for what great and iuſt cauſes God hath made them.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1.</hi> Firſt both are called lights, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is manifeſt, that in kinde they are brought forth, that they may encreaſe and make perfecte the lighte.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> Secondly, when as both do ſhew lyghte, ſo notwithſtandinge are the offices of theire geuinge lighte diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> one moſte clearly doth ſhyne, and doth ſtrayghtwayes drme awaye all darkenes: the other doth not ſhyne ſo clearly, and doth admitte ſome darknes although it doth make the ſame ſomwhat leſſe. 1. cor. 15. Thee is one maner lyghte of the Sonne another of the Mone, another of the Starres</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3.</hi> Thirdlye this dyuerſe power in geuinge lighte, is the cauſe that the one ſhyninge it is day, the other ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning it is night. Which reaſon euen in Moiſes wordes is expreſſed.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:6039:6"/>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4.</hi> Fourthly this diuerſitie in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing light bringeth to paſſe that men alſo may diſcerne theire deedes, and may appoynte the day to labour, the night to reſt: yea and brute beaſtes do appoynt to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues a certayne diffe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rence. Pſalme. <hi>10.</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. He hath made the Moone for certayne ſeaſons and the Sonne knoweth his goinge downe. Thou makeſt darknes &amp; it is nighter in it go abroade all the beaſtes of the wood, the Lyons roaring gape after their praye, that they may ſeke theire meat at God. The Sonne riſeth, and they are gathered back and lye down in theire dennes, man goeth out to his worke and to his laboure vntill the eueninge.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <hi>5.</hi> Fiftly. The Sonne is ſo made of god that it warmeth and dryeth: The Moone doth gently make colde and moyſte. Which temperature is ſo ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie in theſe inferior thinges, that without it neither liuinge creatures,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:6039:6"/>neither any thinges els mighte abide, Peraduenture y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſte lighte mighte haue ſufficed, to note the difference be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>twene lighte and darknes: but it was conuenient that newe bodies ſhoulde be broughte foorth, in which other &amp; greater force ſhoulde be, to nouriſhe and preſerue thoſe thinges which are in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earthe. And therfore aſwell with the heate and drineſſe of the Sonne, as with the colde and moyſtnes of the Moone all things in the wombe of the earth are nouriſhed, broughte forthe, take theire increaſe, and ſo all generation and nutrunente floweth from them into theſe inferior things.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <hi>6.</hi> Sixtly: Moreouer, the motions of the Sonne &amp; Mone chiefly, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by euery day they are caried and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caried from the eaſt into the weſt, in certayne ſpaces of tymes, and from the ſouthe towarde the northe, do ſhew a greate commoditie. For not onely light and darkenes, but alſo
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:6039:7"/>heate and colde, with a certayne moſt apte proportion are diſperſed abroade otherwhyle by theſe regions, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whyle by other regions of the world: which thinges as they are neceſſarie to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good conſtitutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of mens bodies, ſo do they more auayle then can be ſpoken to the alteration of the earthe if ſelfe, and to the ordinarie encreaſſe of all thinges that come forthe in it. Nether yet coulde the earthe, or men abyde, withoute ceaſſinge in one place continuall lighte or continuall dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, or els continuall heate or conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall colde: wherefore euen moſte neceſſarie was this moderatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which followeth thorow the appoynted mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the heauenly bodies.</p>
            <p n="7">
               <hi>7.</hi> Seuenthly. Out of theſe things it appeareth howe the Sonne and the Moone are, according to the ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge of Moſes, for certayne ſeaſons, and for dayes and for yeares. The dayly and moſte ſwifte motion from
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:6039:7"/>the Eaſt into the Weſt doth deſcribe vnto vs dayes and nightes: and that ſame more ſlowe motion from the South into the North doth deſcribe vnto vs yeares, and the parts of the yeare, that is to ſay, the Springe, the Sommer, the Autumne and Winter with theire effectes. And ſo we doo counte and diſtinguiſhe tymes, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge to the diuerſitie of ſuch maner of motions: ſo that it is not altogether ſayd amiſſe of the Philoſophers, that Tune, is the numbringe of motion. And vnto onely man it is geuen, as a greate benefite, to be able to note thoſe motions, and to gather the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of tymes by them.</p>
            <p n="8">
               <hi>8.</hi> Eyghtly. The Sonne and the Mone are for toke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s vnto men, which happeneth two maner of wayes.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1.</hi> The one, when as by a certayne ordinarie reaſon they ſtande ſtill, goe forwarde, or goe backwarde: and ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther are ioyned together, or are oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:6039:8"/>or do ſuffer eclipſe: alſo when they ſhewe forthe raynebowes or miſtye circles about the Sonne, Moone or Starres, to be ſene, by which things fayre wether, tempeſtes, and many effectes are wonte to folowe in the earth, which becauſe with longe tyme and diligent markinge they are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued, and therfore may nowe &amp; than be alſo ſoreſene of vs, let the place of Mathew. cha. <hi>16.</hi> as concerninge the heauen lokinge redde be added.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> The other, ſome thinges are ſene to happen in the Sonne and Moone contrarie to the courſe of nature, the which are wonte to portend or ſhewe ſomething to mankind, &amp; to denounce the anger or merey of God towardes vs. The Sonne and the Mone ſtode vmnoueable, while Iehoſue did ouer come: Ioſue <hi>10.</hi> That Ezechias the kinge mighte knowe that he ſhoulde recouer his healthe, both the Sonne and the ſhadowe in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dyall went back
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:6039:8"/>
               <hi>2.</hi> Kynges. <hi>20.</hi> That Eclipſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Son worthie of remembraunce, at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> death of Chriſt happened contrarie to na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall order, Auguſtine bearinge wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in the <hi>80.</hi> epiſtle to Heſychius, &amp; in his boke <hi>De ciuitate Dei</hi> the <hi>3.</hi> boke chapt. <hi>15.</hi> Hierome vpon Mathew. &amp;c. and the writers of hiſtories do ſhew many things in their commentaries. Of theſe thinges in generall Chriſte ſaieth Luke <hi>21.</hi> There ſhalbe ſignes in the Sonne and in the Moone and in the Starres &amp;c. nether are there wan tynge ſome, amonge whom is Iuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius Africanus, which do interprete the Sonne &amp; the Mone to be ſignes, becauſe aſwell thoſe that ſayle in the ſea, as thoſe which trauell in the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dernes, haue regarde vnto them, and by their guidaunce they learne how they muſte directe theire iorney. And thus much of the offices of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Sonne and the Mone.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Of the ſeco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Queſtion.</note>¶ As touchinge the ſeconde queſtion
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:6039:9"/>whether that there be ſeuerall circles in heauen, and the ſame be driuen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boute with a certayne motion. Nowe let vs diſcourſe, and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in fewe words. The holy ſcriptures do ſeme to allow the rounde fourme of the worlde as deſcribed with a circle, when as Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbes <hi>8.</hi> the heauenly wiſedome, that is, the Sonne of God ſpeaketh thus: Before the mountaynes wer founded and before the hilles. I am fourmed. As yet he had not made the erth and thoſe thinges that are without it and the head of the duſte of the rounde worlde: when he did prepare the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens I was preſente, and when he did deſcribe the circle vpon the face of the depth. If there be any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whome theſe wordes do not ſatiſfie, let him heare experience it ſelfe: which dothe playnely ſhewe, how y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Sonne with his dayly motion dothe paynte forthe a circle in heauen, ſo that we maye in deede perceaue the Sonne to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyned
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:6039:9"/>in a certayne roundell or circle. The which alſo the Preacher. chapter 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> hath expreſſed. The earth (ſaith he) ſtandeth for euer, the Sonne ariſeth, and the Sonne goeth downe, and he goeth to his place. where he may a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yſe, he goeth ouer to the ſouthe, and turneth to the north. The winde tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth rounde, whiſketh about, and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth forthe, and by his circuites it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turneth agayne.</p>
            <p>That there are diſtinct circles, the ſituation of the Starres do mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtlye ſhewe, when as ſome are in an higher place and ſome in a lower: beſide that we do playnly ſe that ſome Starres are caried about more ſwift<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly and ſome more ſlowly. As for the number of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> circles the ſcripture doth not define them: and otherwiſe doth the olde Aſtronomers, otherwiſe doth the newe determine: yea and not at this preſent amongeſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Aſtronomers that nowe be, is there any agrement
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:6039:10"/>therof. But that they be moued by p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſcripte lawes or order, it is both found by the longe obſeruatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of tymes, and the ſcripture doth not diſſemble it. For that I maye omitte the words of the preacher laſtly rehearſed, thus do we read Pſal. <hi>104.</hi> He hath made y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Mone for apoynted ſeaſons, and the Sonne knoweth his going downe. Iob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 31. it is ſaied, The Mone moueably going. and the <hi>38.</hi> chapter. God alone is ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed to bringe to p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>e verie greate thinges by his prouidence, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongeſt the reſt to ſette lawes alſo to the motio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of the Starres; in which, man can performe nothing. Wat thou bynde (ſaieth he) the ſweete influen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the ſeauen Starres?<note place="margin">38.</note> or wilt thou let looſe the force attractiue of Orion: or if thou ſhalt be able to being the conſtellation of Mazaroth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſeaſon? or wilt thou be able to leade the North ſtarre wyth hys children<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> knoweſt thou the lawes of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:6039:10"/>that thou mayeſt ſhewe forth the dominion thereof vpon the earth? But Chryſoſtome in the <hi>14.</hi> homilie vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the epiſtell to the Hebrewes doth denye the heauen to be of a rounde fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure, or to be moued: leaninge to thoſe wordes wherewith it is ſaied Hebr. 8. That Chriſt the highe Prieſt ſittinge at the right hand of maieſtie, is a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of holie thinges, and of the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle that God hath pighte, and not man. There he noteth heauen to to be called pighte or fixed. But it is manifeſt, that in that place mention is made of the outmoſte or higheſt heauen, in the which Chriſt ſitteth at the right hand of his father: and I do diſcourſe of the firmament in which the Starres are placed. But to rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of theſe matters, eyther curiouſly or contentiouſly, Auguſtine vpon Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſis <hi>after the letter. lib. 2. cap. 9. &amp; 10.</hi> ſuppoſeth it to be more then neadeth, ſpecially ſith the knowledge of ſuche
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:6039:11"/>matters doth littell or nothinge auaile to godlines.</p>
            <p>¶ Let vs go forwarde to the thirde queſtion. It is apparaunte that this opinion came firſt from Pythagoras: that is to ſay, that the celeſtiall circles becauſe they be moſt large and ſet one vpon another, and that they all in like maner are driuen aboute continually with a certen moderatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: geue a moſte ſwete ſounde, and a playne muſicall harmonie: <hi>Cicero in ſomnio Scipionis</hi> and other wirters make mention of it. Some ſinatterers in diuinitie, to the ende that that lie may be ſmothed, do bringe forthe theſe wordes of the <hi>38.</hi> of Iob. Who ſhall ſhew the reaſon of the heauens, or who ſhall make the concente or tune of the heauens to ſleepe? But in fewe woordes I aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere, denyinge ſimply any conſent or tune to be brought out of the moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly circles. The reaſons of the Pithagoreans are ouerthrowe
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:6039:11"/>with ſmall adoe: but leſt I ſhould leſe tyme in this matter, I had rather the confutation ſhoulde be gathered out of Ariſtotle <hi>de coelo lib. 2. cap. 9.</hi> than to be l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ked for of me. And wheras it is certayne that Pithagoras broughte forthe almoſt all his opinions in cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne darke ſenſes or allegories: it is more probable that he woulde with ſuche excogitate or depe reaſon ſhewe and commende the wonderfull obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and agrement of all thinges, but chiefly of heauenly creatures, in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forminge diligently the dueties which te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de to the ſettinge forth of the power and prouidence of God, than any out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde or corporall conce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, as we may perceaue in muſical inſtrumentes. In which ſenſe we are accuſtomed to ſave in a Church, ſchole, or commonwelth well ordered, in which euerie one do theire dutie with greate concorde, that there is a certayne very beautifull har<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>monie to be ſene. Furthermore that
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:6039:12"/>place in Iob is not faithfully tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted accordinge to the truthe of the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brue, but thus it oughte rather to be read: Who ſhal number the cloudes in wiſdom, or who ſhal make the bottels of heauen to reſt? where the worde <hi>Nebel</hi> ſignifieth a waterbudge or a bot<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tell, and ſo thoſe which are moſt ſkil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Hebricians do note in that place. And althoughe otherwhile the ſame worde do ſignifie a muſicall inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dinge becauſe words goe before of the cloudes, out of which as out of bottels, it is manifeſt that water is largely powred, the reaſon of the texte dothe require, that ſo as I ſaye it muſte be expounded. Let no man therfore raſhly abuſe the wordes of the ſcripture to eſtabliſhe an abſurd or vnlikely opinion.</p>
            <p>The fourthe queſtion is, whether the Starres haue lyfe? This queſtion I do not therfore onely touche, becauſe Plato in <hi>Timaeo</hi> and his folowers,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:6039:12"/>
               <hi>Cicero</hi> ſhewinge the ſame in <hi>lib. 2. De Natura deorum,</hi> do defyne the Sonne the Moone and the other Starres to be liuinge thinges endued with mynd and reaſon, and to feede of humors which euery day they drawe vpward, finally to be Gods: but alſo becauſe the ſcripture doth witneſſe, that there were ſome among the Iewes did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue the like thinges, for <hi>2.</hi> kinges <hi>23.</hi> chapiter it is ſhewed, that ſome did burn ince<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſe to the Sonne, the Moone the Planetes, and the whole hoſte of Heauen: and that there were horſes and charrets dedicated to the Sunne: Moreouer becauſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>Manichaei</hi> a kinde of heretiques, beſides the ſtraunge dotinge dreames, which Auguſtine a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſte <hi>Fauſtus Manicheus libr. 20. cap. 9.</hi> doth wryte that they inue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted of the Sonne and the Moone, they thought alſo that they ought to be worſhipped: the which is gathered out of Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine. <hi>Epiſtola 74. ad Deuteriu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> epiſcopum,</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:6039:13"/>agaynſte <hi>Fauſtus Manichaeus lib. 5. cap. 40.</hi> and <hi>De Geneſi contra Manichaeos lib. 1. cap. 3. lib. 2. cap. 25.</hi> alſo <hi>Diſputatione prima contra Fortunatuni.</hi> But that the Starres by no meanes are to be wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhipped euery man by him ſelfe maye determine, which doth onely marke the ſcripture to ſhewe playnlye that they are creatures made of God in a certen tyme. And it is manifeſt, that the honoure which is due to the Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator, by no meanes oughte to be geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the Creatures, Romans <hi>1.</hi> &amp;c. And Ioſias the kinge is openly prayſed <hi>2.</hi> kinges <hi>23.</hi> which did take awaye ſuch idolatrous cuſtomes. Ier. alſo the <hi>7.</hi> and <hi>44.</hi> chapters doth moſt ſharply chide, &amp; threateneth greuouſe puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes to them which did ſacrifice to the Starres: ſpecially ſith that <hi>Deute. 17.</hi> the worſhippinge of Heauenly bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies whatſoeuer they were is playnly forbidden, and the tranſgreſſors are commaunded to be puniſhed with the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:6039:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>payne of ſtoninge. Men were induced to ſo greate idolatrie at that tyme ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, that they did falſely ſuſpecte, that the Starres had lyfe, and were delighted with falſe worſhip. But that they haue not lyfe appeareth by this, that in <hi>Geneſis</hi> the <hi>1.</hi> and <hi>9.</hi> chapters, where thoſe thinges are reckened vp, vnto whom a lyuinge ſoule is geuen: onely men, fiſhes, byrdes, crepinge thinges and liuinge thinges remay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninge vpon the earth, are rehearſed: but the Starres are excluded out of that number. And that man onely is endued with reaſon, and alſo amonge bodily ſubſtances, is more euidente, than that it oughte to be proued with any argumentes: which reaſone will worthely ſuffiſe vnto wittes not ouer curiouſe. To gather, by theire motion or by theire certayne offices, that they haue lyfe, it is not neceſſarie: for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thinges deſtitute of lyfe, bothe do naturally, and alſo ſuffer: as artificial
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:6039:14"/>fier ſhineth, burneth, kindleth, moueth and is moued: alſo water floweth, is moued with great viole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce or force &amp;c. alſo pretiouſe ſtones, herbes and other ſymples haue theire force: and yet no man for theſe conſiderations will attribute lyfe to them. And wher as the ſcripture doth ſaye, the Sunne knoweth his goinge downe, let the Heauens be glad, and let the Earthe reioyce &amp;c. theſe muſt be taken as ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by a metaphor or proſopei, as alſo ful oft the Autors of holy bokes accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomably vſe ſuch kynd of figurs. As example, Pſal. <hi>114.</hi> The ſea ſaw it &amp; fled. Iordade was driuen backward. The Mountanes leaped as ra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mes, &amp; the litle hills as la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mes, what meaneſt thou o Sea that thou diddeſt flye &amp;c. Therfore rightly do Lactantius <hi>Fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mianus. lib. 2. inſtitutionu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> diuinarum cap. 5.</hi> Hierome expoundinge the 45. chap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter of Eſay. <hi>Baſil. in lib. de opere ſeptem dierum.</hi> and <hi>Damaſcenus</hi> folowing him
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:6039:14"/>
               <hi>libr. 2. de Orthodoxa fide cap. 6.</hi> deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myne that the Starres are withoute lyfe and do lacke ſenſe. And although Auguſt. who was noſeled in the Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonicall diſcipline, doth ſeeme in <hi>Enchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridio ad Lauréntium and de Geneſi ad li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lib. 2 cap. 18.</hi> to leaue it in doubte: yet in his booke <hi>ad Oroſium contra Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcillianiſtas &amp; Origeniſtas</hi> he doth ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly ſay thus: furthermore as touching the Sonne and the Moone and the reſt of the Starres, that they be celeſtiall bodies we ſee, but that they be liuinge bodies we ſee not. Where after a few wordes he addeth, theſe thinges are not ſo ſet out in the ſcriptures, that the knowledge of them is commended vnto vs. This is morcouer to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, that in his retractations lib. <hi>2.</hi> whereas certayne things are ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken agaynſte <hi>Fauſtus Manichaeus libr. 14.</hi> touchinge the Sonne and the Moone, as thoughe they had ſenſe and therfore exalted diuers theire
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:6039:15"/>worſhippers, he geueth this admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that thoſe wordes are to be take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as ſpoken <hi>Metaphorically.</hi> And he wrot theſe bookes, after them in the which he ſeemed to doubte. Which thinges ſeinge they are ſo, it is euidente that <hi>Origenes</hi> which goeth altogether in the ſteps of the Platonians and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounceth that the Stars haue lyfe, is in no wife to be harkened to. And I am in doubte that that, which is thought to be, is not the minde of the Philoſophers: for it is to be beleued that they did not thinke that in deede the Starres were indued with lyfe, as we ſaye that men, birdes, fiſhes, and ſuch lyke are: but rather that they ſpake ſo by a <hi>Metaphor</hi> or els truely that by an <hi>Allegorie</hi> they fayned that there was life &amp; reaſon in the ſtarres: whereby they might more euidently declare, that in a moſt decent order, and as it were in a meaſure they do finiſh theire motions, euen as though
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:6039:15"/>after the maner of men, they were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued with reaſon.</p>
            <p>Now laſtly it is expedient that I ſhould goe thorow with the fift que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, Whether the ſtarres and the ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtiall motions do bring to paſſe any thing vpon theſe inferiour bodies. It is to be vnderſtanded that about the yeare <hi>380.</hi> (in which ſeaſon Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine liued) there was a certaine Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niard named Priſcillianus, which di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperſed thorow the Churches many falſe opinions taken partly of the he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retikes called <hi>Gnoſtici,</hi> partely of the heretikes called <hi>Manichaei:</hi> and among the reſt, he taughte that the doinges of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were gouerned by the motions of the ſtarres, and that the bodie of man was ſo compou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded that certaine ſignes of the circle of the Zodiac did rule certaine partes &amp; members: and ſome other things like theſe. Neither are ther wanting at theſe dayes, ſome which are delighted with ſuch fooliſh
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:6039:16"/>toyes. I haue alſo marked ſome of the ſchoole writers to graunt, that the ſtarres do moue and encline the wils of men.</p>
            <p>That I may therfore aunſwere the queſtion, and encounter vnſauery er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, it is meete to diſtinguiſh the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour bodies: for there are ſome which are brought forth &amp; haue their being in the ayer, the carth, the water, and the ſame partly are without life, partly haue life, hauing only a vege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatiue or els a ſenſitiue life. The other I vnderſtand to be mens bodies: and ſo whole man conſiſting of ſoule and bodie, and not vegetatiue or ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue onely, but alſo endued with rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. As touching the inferiour bodies of the former kinde, as there is great diuerſitie of them, ſo a good parte of them ſeemeth to conſiſt &amp; to be gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with the motion and power of the heauenly bodies: the which ſome do endeuour to proue with ſome argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:6039:16"/>and examples. Firſt: Thoſe Meteores or high thinges (ſay they) which are ſeene in the ayre, as comets or blaſing ſtarres, miſty circles about the Sonne, Mone, or Starres, light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, thunders, raine, haile, do chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie come from the ſtarres, whereby ſome obſeruing the ſituation of the ſta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>res, do foreſhew ſuch Meteors to appeare. And Ariſtotle in his firſt booke of Meteors the ſecond chapter, amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g principles doth determine, that it is to be graunted, that thoſe things which happen in the inferiour worlde, ought to be eſteemed as taken of the motion and efficacie of the celeſtiall circles. Secondly, Thoſe thinges which grow out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth as hearbs, trees, fruites, corne, and ſuch like, all men holde as a thing confeſſed, to be verie much holpen by the warmth of the Sonne and the moyſtnes of the Moone: and it is found by proofe that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>cetie doth follow where the deaw
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:6039:17"/>or raine wanteth, yea and the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture it ſelfe doth witneſſe it. <hi>2.</hi> Sam. <hi>23.</hi> and <hi>1.</hi> Kings. <hi>17.</hi> Thirdly. The bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of all liuing thinges are foſtered and nouriſhed wyth the warmth of the Sun: moreouer accordinge to the motion of the Moone they are affer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>undrie chaunges, of which ſort is, that humors chiefly are ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>while encreaſed ſomwhile diminiſhed. Moreouer the Sunne is thought to helpe to generation; in ſo much that ſome men haue not fear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> to ſay that man is engendred of the Sunne and the Moone. Many thinges alſo are ſayd of the offices of the Sunne and Moone, whereby theſe things ſeeme to be eſtabliſhed. Fourthly. Inume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable thinges there are, which with the Sunne the Moone, &amp; the ſtarres do communicate diuerſe affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, and haue a certeine <hi>Synpathia</hi> or like affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or paſſion with them. The ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gold and lupine being hear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es, are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:6039:17"/>moued about with the ſon. Crabbes, oyſters, cockels, and the fiſhe called <hi>Echinus,</hi> are filled whyle the Moone encreaſeth, contrary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſe when ſhe is miniſhed, there is leſſe fiſhe in them. Moreouer the Moone doth drawe to, and driue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the returninge tides of the ſea, whereof more is to be ſeene in Plin. lib. <hi>2.</hi> chapters <hi>4.41.97.98.99.100.101.</hi> alſo lib. <hi>18.</hi> cap. <hi>27.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Although theſe thinges are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably ſpoken, yet wee muſte defyne that the thinges whyche happen in theſe inferiour bodies, are by no wayes broughte to paſſe by the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of the celeſtiall bodies or of the Starres. The reaſons are in rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dines.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1</hi> Vnto God alone, who is the onely author of all good things, and doth create nothinge in vayne, but gouerneth the thynges whyche he hath created by hys prouidence, all
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:6039:18"/>theſe effectes oughte to be aſcribed: as alſo he verely hath once geuen to inferior thynges thoſe powers and qualities from the beginninge, that of their owne nature by themſelues they ſhould bring foorth ſuch effecte and ſhould receiue no helpe of other thinges. The which in the confuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the former argumentes I will make manifeſte by the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2</hi> If the offices of the Sunne the Moone and Starres be nombred, it is not expreſly found in the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, that it is committed vnto them, that they ſhoulde imparte or infuſe anye actions into theſe infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour bodyes by themſelues or by their motion: but that chiefelye is attributed to them, that they geue light, they rule the day &amp; the nighte, they diſcerne lighte from darkenes, they are for ſignes, finally they are for ſeaſons for dayes and for yeares</p>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:6039:18"/>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3</hi> But if any thinge may be attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted vnto them, it may not be at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed but as to ſecond cauſes, and the ſame very farre of, of which ther is no vſe but when, where, howe farre, and how it ſhall ſeeme good to God himſelfe which is the firſt cauſe, and the cauſe of cauſes. And ſo the Sunne, the Moone, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Stars ſhall ſcarcely be ſet in that place, in which inſtrume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tall cauſes are wont to be ſet. It is manifeſt that inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall thinges by them ſelues do nothing, and do onely ſo far profit, as by men they are put to it: And whereas men may hardly want in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumentall thinges, God truly eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> without theſe doth bringe to paſſe euery thinge mightely and quickly. Medicines are vſed for to recouer health: neuertheleſſe that is a profe, that by them ſelues they do nothing, becauſe many tymes in vayne they are geuen, the diſeaſes in no caſe
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:6039:19"/>being driuen away: yea God often tymes hath reſtored health euen wythout medicine. Wherefore the Sonne the Moone &amp; the Starres, it they ſeeme to be of anye force to heate or colde, to generation or cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, or els to any other action, ſure it is that by themſelues they performe none of theſe thinges, and without them the like may come from ſome other thinge, other cauſes and h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>es comming to: but of God him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> are all things made perfect, and (if I may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e ſaye) thorowly fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed. One planteth, another wate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, but only God geueth the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe: and neyther they which plant or water are any thinge, but God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone is all in all. <hi>1 Cor. 3.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1</hi> Now will I anſwere to theire argumentes in order. As co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning the Meteores, it is falſe, that they come by the force of the Starres. Firſt, al their matter is beleued to be
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:6039:19"/>brought forth out of theſe inferiour thinges: and there is a certain force in the earth it ſelf to caſt out vapors &amp; what ſoeuer is of that ſort. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer, ſuch matter abideth nere vs in the ayre, very farre of fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſtars, and is freely, and at libertie, moued, or driuen, vntill it haue taken ſome conuenient forme. Beſides that, of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes the mater being gathered together, is ſodenly diſſeuered, and againe, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is thought not to be, ſome of the Meteores come foorth. As for the Cometes, the Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers themſelues dare not aſcribe vnto the ſtarres. Many of them af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming (among whom is Seneca) that they are peculiar ſtars, ſhining by the comma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dement of the higheſt God, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they may ſhew ſome ſtrange thing vnto men. Beſides that, what great varietie of the Thunder and Lightning is there: we, contrary to the lawes of the philoſophers, haue
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:6039:20"/>felte them, euen in the middeſt of winter, and in colde Regions, as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo that Snowes haue fallen often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times in ſummer.</p>
            <p>Furthermore the violence of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> light<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ning is maruelous wherwith huge building are caſte downe, money is melted, the lether of the purſe being vnhurt: the bone of the legge is bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, &amp; the fleſh without, remayning whole: a man ſtaine, and no ſigne of a wounde. Of theſe I ſay, and the like, what reaſon (I pray you) will they geue? Wherfore Ariſtotle him ſelfe graunteth in the beginninge of his meteorology, that there are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thinges ſpoaken of this matter, doubtfull and vncertaine, and ſome things to be ſo ſo touched. And if o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwhile they doe foreſhew a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met, or ſome ſuch thing to appeare, yet we muſt ſee again, how oft they are deceaued, and doe deceaue: how ofte in like maner ſuch thinges are
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:6039:20"/>ſeene, when as no man hath ſhewed any thing afore, ſo that no ſuch kind of predictions are nothing els, but light and vncertaine coniectures.</p>
            <p>Finally, whereas Ariſtotle doth define that all theſe inferior bodies are moued and gouernd by the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the celeſtiall bodies, we will take it as ſpoken of him, which hath bent his minde to ſearch out onelye naturall cauſes, and humaine wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. As for the true God, the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor and gouerner of all thinges, he neuer did know. Whileſt he doth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde and looke vpon the creatures more then right was, he coulde not aſcend to the Creator himſelf, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of it commeth, that the ſelfe ſame A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſtotle hath defyned, that the world was not made in time, but that it is eternall, and many other things con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trary to the truth of the holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. Let vs therfore follow the ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, which manifeſtlye doe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:6039:21"/>that all meteors are formed &amp; ſhewed forth by God alone, when and how it pleaſeth him. God is ſaid to geue raine, <hi>Pſal. 147. Amos. 4. Mat. 5. Act. 14.</hi> to bring the winds out of his treaſures, <hi>Pſal. 135.</hi> to ſtirre vp a ſhowrie ſtorme, which lifteth vp y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> waues of the ſea, &amp; throweth down the ſhippes with a vehement force. And ſtraight way againe, commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the tempeſtes to ceaſe, and the waues to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>il. <hi>Pſal 107.</hi> Alſo. <hi>Iob. 37</hi> God hath thundered with his voice doing maruels, and great thinges, we not knowing how they be done, He ſpeaketh to the ſnow that it may be vpon the earth. Alſo out of his priuie chambers co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth the whirle-winde, and out of the ſeatterings of the cloudes his colde. By the breath of God the froſt is geeuen, and the bredth of waters is frozen. Beſide that, for the watring of the earth he weryeth the cloudes, and againe, he
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:6039:21"/>driueth away the cloudes with his light, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>Moreouer, the earthquake when Chriſt was in dying, <hi>Mat. 28.</hi> &amp; thoſe which are ſhewed to come before the day of the laſt iudgement, <hi>Matt. 24. Luke 21.</hi> As alſo <hi>Act. 4.</hi> and <hi>16.</hi> are written that they ſhall be wrought by the power of God.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2</hi> To the ſecond argument wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with it is ſaid that hearbes, trees, and fruites are very much holpen with the heate of the ſunne, &amp; moiſt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes of the moone: it may be graun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that by ſome meanes they are helped. But that they are the cauſe that they grow, or ſpring foorth ſo largely as they doe, that I doe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly deny. For euen the earth it ſelfe doth within nouriſh a certaine natiue heate: Beſide that, euen through the ſame earth, waters are ſhed abroade here and there, as it were in vaines, the which we muſt
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:6039:22"/>graunt no leſſe, nay rather becauſe they are nigher, more to auaile then the ſunne or the moone. What ſay you to this, that God oftentimes, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen without dewe or raine, doth make the ground fruitfull, and ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth plentie of corne, chieflye in E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gipt, where the common watering chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceth not with raines, but with the yearely ouerflowing of Nilus, Plinie witneſſing it, <hi>Lib. 5. cap. 9.</hi> and <hi>lib. 18. cap. 18,</hi> and other wryters.</p>
            <p>Farthermore, the dearth of corne is ſeene ſometime euen then, when raine inough and inough hath falne before. For God puniſheth the ſins of men by what meanes he liſteth. Againe, when it lyketh him, ſodenly and in very great drought, hee gee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth aboundance of all thinges, the which in the time of Elias and Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zeus and many other times is mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked. <hi>1. Kin. 17.18.2. Kin. 18.</hi> &amp; <hi>Pſal, 107.</hi> it is plainly ſaid, that God turneth
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:6039:22"/>Riuers into a wilderneſſe, and the water ſpringes into a thirſtie or drie place. And alſo he chaungeth a fruitefull lande into barraineneſſe, for the wickednes of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that dwell therein. And againe, he chaungeth the wilderneſſe into a poole of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and a drie lande into water ſpringes &amp;c. Wherefore with great co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſent haue the fathers taught that it ought not to be grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted that with the heate or helpe of the Sunne any thinges here are increaſed, or els come forth. Baſilius of the ſixe day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>workes, the firſt homilie, the Lorde ſaith: let the earth bring forth green herbe. By it ſelfe let it bring foorth herbe, needing the helpe of no other thing at all. For becauſe ſome think the Sunne to be the cauſe of thoſe things which grow out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth, by meanes of the attraction of the warmth that draweth the force of which is in the depth of the earth,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:6039:23"/>to the rimme or outſide, euen there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore more auncient is the making of the earth than of the ſunne. With which error let them that be decea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, ceaſe to adore the Sunne, as if hee gaue the cauſe of life. If ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they wil beleeue, that before his generation or beginning, all thinges about the earth were made, let them alſo remitte the vnmeaſurable ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of him: thinking thus, that hee is younger than herbes and hay, as touching his generation. Chriſoſt. is of his opinion, the <hi>5.</hi> Homilie vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Geneſ. The holy ſcripture (ſaith he) reprouing the vnthankefulneſſe that ſhould be of men, as it doth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare all thinges, ſo doth it ſhew vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs the order of things made, that it might brydle the trit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ings and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages of them, which commend the vanities of their own inuentions, &amp; dare ſaye that the operation of the Sun is neceſſary to the encreaſe of
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:6039:23"/>fruites, and there are other which go about to aſcribe the ſame to the ſtarres. Therfore the holy ghoſt tea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cheth vs that before the making of theſe elementes, the earth, obaying both the word &amp; commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dement of God, hath brought forth all ſeedes, hauing neede of none other thing to worke with it. Many things folow to the ſame purpoſe, aſwel in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> place as in the <hi>6.</hi> Hom. Neither doth Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe diſſeute, or diſagree with theſe in his <hi>3.</hi> boke of the ſix day workes, <hi>c. 6.</hi> &amp; <hi>Lib. 4. c. 1. 2.</hi> In ſumme they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce it to be the propertie of Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tils and heathen people, to attribute the generation, or bringinge forth of things to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Son, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moone or ſtars.</p>
            <p>For there are very many thinges to be together co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidered in the work of the generatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of things growing out of the earth, firſt and formoſte, ſeedes, &amp; thoſe thinges which haue a ſtedy power in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which muſt be
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:6039:24"/>added for becauſe of thoſe thinges which are thoughte to come vp of their own accorde: then the diuers qualities of the earth it ſelfe, that is added that heate, moiſtnes, fatnes, and the reſt like vnto theſe: Beſide that, men and cattle, &amp; thoſe thinges which come by the diligence and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours of men, as dunging, cutting, and diuers workes of huſbandrie. And after all theſe, raine, cleerenes of the aire, Sunſhining, ſpeciallie when the time of ripenes is at hand But aſwell afore, as after all this, the louing kindneſſe and bleſſing of God him ſelfe, which alone doeth geue encreaſe, without the which al the reſt are in vaine.</p>
            <p>Therefore Chriſoſtome in his 6. homilie, both ſay that the Gentiles doe greeuouſly offende, which haue in ſuch admiration, and are ſo aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied at the elemente of the Sunne, and looke not further, neither doe
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:6039:24"/>praiſe the maker thereof. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, after that athe earth had broght forth all kinde of ſeedes, and had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken her Artire and Decking, this elemente of the Sunne was made, that hereafter no man may ſay that without the operation of the Sunne the Fruites of the Earth are not perfect.</p>
            <p>To this place belong the Canons <hi>73.74.75.</hi> gathered out of the Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nodes of the Eaſt by Martine, Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoppe of Braccara: wherewith is forbidden vnto Chriſtians to folow the traditions of the Gentils, in ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruing or worſhipping the eleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, or the courſes of the moone or ſtars, or the vaine deceate of ſinges: For building an houſe, or for to ſowe or plante trees, or to make mariages: Alſo wherwith is forbidden y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ſhould abſtaine from worke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> daies of the Calendes after the maner of the Gentils, or that they ſhould ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:6039:25"/>about their houſes y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> green boughs of Laurell or other trees: And that they ſhould vſe obſeruation in gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring herbes for medicine. The ſame chapters are reherſed <hi>quaſt. 26. can. 5. Non licet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now ſhal you heare ſaint Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine <hi>de Ciuitate Dei, Lib. 5. Cap. 7.</hi> Why doe they chooſe (ſaith he) ſome daies fitte to ſet vines or trees, or to ſowe corne: other ſome dayes to tame or breake cattle, or to let them goe to make or fellow: by meanes wherof their heardes of mares or kine may be fruitefull, and ſuch like?</p>
            <p>If therefore choſen dayes doe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e to theſe things, becauſe the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of the ſtarres hath dominion ouer all earthly bodies, whether they haue life or not life accordinge to the diuerſities of the momentes of times: But them conſider how many thinges without number vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der one poynte of tune, are eyther
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:6039:25"/>borne, or do ſpring, or arebegun: and haue ſuch diuers endings, that they perſuade that theſe obſeruatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s are to be laughed at of euery childe. For who is ſo without vnderſtandinge that he dare ſay that all trees, herbs, beaſtes, ſerpentes, birdes, fiſhes, wormes haue one by one diuers mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ments of beginning? And a litle af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he ſaith: Nether wil they marke, that in the day which they haue cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen to ſowe their field, ſo many corns come into the ground at once: they ſhutte out together, when the corne is ſpronge they growe greene toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, they ſpindle, they begin to looke browne together: and yet of thoſe eares being of the ſame age and of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame ſhutte with the reſt, ſome is ſinitten, ſome the birdes doe deſtroy ſome, men pul away. How wil they ſay that to theſe there were other conſtellations, which they doe ſee to haue ſo diuers endes. So muche
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:6039:26"/>hath he: And in other places hee is exerciſed in the ſame argument: as <hi>Epiſt. 129. ad Iannurium de viribus Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae, de doctrina Chriſtiana Lib. 14. ca. 29. In Enchir. ad Laurentium lib. 1. c. 79.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the expoſition of the <hi>4.</hi> Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to the Galat. where he doth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprete that againſt ſuch obſeruers it is ſaid of the Apoſtle: Ye obſerue Dayes, and Monethes, and times, and yeares. I am afrayed of you leaſte I haue laboured in vayne to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde you. Of theſe thinges then it is ſufficiently manifeſt that in no wiſe it is to be graunted, that by the power of the ſunne, the mone or the ſtarres, thinges in the earth are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendred or brought forth the more plenteouſly. And the holy fathers were very dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in beating of this doctrine which I propounde, into mennes heades, for becauſe of the Gentiles which were full of foule errours.</p>
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:6039:26"/>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3</hi> By theſe thinges it is eaſie to be vnderſtanded what may be ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſayd to the third argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. There abydeth in the bodies of liuing crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures a natiue warmth, the which alſo is nouriſhed with bloud: beſide that, it is ſtirred with certaine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumentes, ſpecially thoſe which worke to concoction ordigeſtion and mouing of the partes: It is alſo ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtayned with meate, drinke, &amp; other helpes beſide, as before alſo I ſayde that in the earth it ſelf there is a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine warmth. And whether they will or not, all men muſt graunte, that to generation ſpecially are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired ſeedes, or thoſe things which haue in them a ſeedie power. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer, that other actions are requy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to come from certain bodies, but before all thinges (as I haue ſayde afore) the will and working of God, as that without the which the reſt are of no waight or moment: &amp; how
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:6039:27"/>abſurde a thing and vnlikely to be true it is, that man is ingendred or begotten of the Sunne and man, euery man of himſelfe doth vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand. Why ſhall any conſideration be iudged to be had of age: What cauſes alſo ſhalbe ſhewed: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore men and women of luſty bodies and hauing al their members whole and ſound, are found to be vnfrutful and barrayne.</p>
            <p>Beſides this, if fruite of the body come by the ſunne, how hapneth it that the procreation of children is ac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted among the ſingular benefits of God? Why did <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nna the wife of Eicana, and other ſaintes require children to be geuen them of God? Or is there any that will builde vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this, that ſoules are put into bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies by the Sunne, which it ſelfe is without ſoule. Let then this hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine and carnall philoſophie geue. place, and let all men acknowledge
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:6039:27"/>the facultie and benefite of genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, yea and power alſo to put ſoules into the bodies to be receaued, not of the Sunne, the Mone, or any ſtars, but of God alone, which hath wiſely made the members of generation.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4</hi> The fourth argument is very weake. For it doth not follow, for becauſe that ſome thinges haue like affections with the Moone, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they take the ſame of the Moone: But this ſhalbe more aptly ſaide, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> looke whence ſuch affections come to the Moone, euen from thence alſo come the like affections in other thinges, which by them ſelues, and of their own nature doe containe the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninges of chaunges &amp; diuers quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. No man will rightly ſay, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that the moſt parte of liuinge creatures ſlepe in the night, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo doe certaine other thinges at the ſame tune and after the ſame maner that men are wonte to doe the like,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:6039:28"/>that they take this facultie of men. With what right then ſhall wee af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme that ſuch thinges as are incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed or diminiſhed when the Moone encreaſeth or diminiſheth, or els are chaunged by any other meanes, that they take the cauſe of this chaunge by the Moone? But theſe things ſhal ſuffice as touching the power of the heauenly bodies, vpon the infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior bodies which lack reaſon.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <hi>5</hi> Now remaineth that I ſhould ſhew what force thoſe thinges (that is, the Sunne, the Moone and the Starres) haue ouer men which are indued with reaſon. The Priſcilli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aniſtes (as I ſayd before) and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of the Schooledoctors of the ſame opinion, inferpreting y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſeconde booke of ſentences of Petrus Lom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bardus <hi>Diſtinct. 14.</hi> haue attributed to the Starres more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> right was.</p>
            <p>Two principall pointes muſt here be diſcourſed. The one whether the
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:6039:28"/>of man be moued by the power of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Starres? The other whether any certaintie of mans life, and the good or euill actions in the ſame may bee forſhewed by the poſition of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtars? As touching the former queſtion, I will plainly proue with diuers rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, that in no wiſe it is to be grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that the will of man is moued to doe anye thing by the force of the Starres.</p>
            <p>Firſtly, If it like you to behold the principall cauſe wherwith many are moued to affirme the contrarie, you ſhall finde it very weke. They were perſwaded that all inferior bodyes without exception, were diuerſly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected by the Starres: that being graunted, they went further and ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered: when as the bodies were ſo affected, the organes or inſtruments themſelues of the ſences ſet here &amp; there in the bodies, were affected al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo: and of the inſtrumentes affected,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:6039:29"/>it ſeemeth neceſſarie that the ſences themſelues likewiſe ſhould be moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued: as we ſee in them, of who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſome partes (ſpecially being within) are hurte nigh their eyes, alſo which are diſeaſed with madneſſe, phre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſie, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholie &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Furthermore, the inſtrumentes &amp; ſences being moued, from thence paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth a certaine force to the vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ding and will. In this order there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and as it were by certaine de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees the will of man ſhalbe moued: or (as they ſay) inclyned by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtars. But I, in the premiſſes, haue ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently ſhewed that the Celeſtiall bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies doe not (as they thinke) worke in theſe inferior bodies, no not in thoſe which are without life, and which are without reaſon. How much leſſe then ſhall they worke in the bodies of men, whom God hath garniſhed with reaſon and iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment aboue all the Creatures that
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:6039:29"/>that liue in the earth? Therefore the Starres doe not one iote bring any thing to paſſe in the vnderſtandinge or will of man.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the holy ſcripture doth plainly attribute to God the inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and gouernmente of mannes harte: that is to ſay, of the vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding and will of man, Prouerb. <hi>21.</hi> As the Riuers of waters ſo the harte of the king is directed by the hande of the Lord, &amp; he doth encline it whether he wil, Prouerb. <hi>16.</hi> The harte of man muſt deuiſe his way, but God will order his going. Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerb. <hi>20.</hi> The goynges of a man are of the Lorde, and howe then ſhall man be able to vnderſtand hys waye. And many ſuche lyke ſenten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces there are. The Scripture alſo doeth in manye places commaunde that we ſhoulde faſhion our will to the will of God whych doth rule our will: and that we ſhoulde al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:6039:30"/>way ſay as ofte as we purpoſe any thing: If the Lord will.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, if the actions of man were diſtinguiſhed, of which it is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt that ſome are Spirituall and inwarde, pertayning to the worſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of God and health of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoules: ſome earthly or outwarde, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to Princely or houſhold go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: ſome to be meane, tending directly neither to good nor ill: we ſhall finde none of theſe of which it may be ſayd, that they are gouerned of the Starres, but rather we muſt graunt that they depende and are moued of God alone. For as God alone doth rule our actions, ſo doth he rule our will.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, no nor the precepts ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen of the obſeruers of the Stars can ſtande firme, or promiſe any cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taintie. For where as they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde to beholde the ſignes of the zodiac in euery bodies natiuitie, in
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:6039:30"/>the ſignes to diſtinguiſh the degrees in the degrees the ſixtieth partes: &amp; in thoſe ſixtie partes the very ſmall diuiſions of minutes or ſcruples: it can not be (as Baſile in his ſixt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milie doth playnly proue, and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine in his fifte booke <hi>De ciuitate Dei. cap. 4</hi> doth confirme) that ſuch diſtinctions of verie ſmale partes ſhould be exactlie inough noted in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> horoſcope or the ſigne aſcendent, and in the Starres partly fixed, partly wandring. How then can be rende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red cauſes (ſaith the ſame Baſile) for the which of two, which are both conceaued and borne in one indiui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible (as I may ſaye) moment of tyme, that the one afterward becom<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth a King, the other a begger? how happeneth if (ſaith Auguſtine in his fift booke <hi>De ciuitate Dei cap. 2.</hi>) that in twinnes, in whome is marked a maruelous conſent of momentes in theire conception and in their birth,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:6039:31"/>and in the other thinges adioyninge to them, that yet there is ſeene a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy great vnlikeneſſe of health, of ſtrength, of maners, and of all their eſtate. The ſame <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tiguſtine in the <hi>4.</hi> chapter addeth a notable erample of very great dinerſitie in all theire ſucceedinges throughout all theire life, of the twinnes Iacob and Eſau out of the <hi>25.</hi> chapter of Geneſis. What ſay you of this, that the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thematicians themſelnes doe teach contraricties, aſwell ofthe forme of the chooſing of the <hi>12.</hi> houſes, (For the oide Mathematicians doe it one way, Ptolomeus anotherway, Ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panus another way, Ioannes Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giomontanus another way,) as of the maner of accounting: and one doth teproue another of errour. By which meanes truely, themſelues doe bewray the bn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>intie of the arte which they profeſſe.</p>
            <p>Fifty, if the governmente of our
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:6039:31"/>actions ſhoulde Depende upon the Starres, many abſurdities woulde follow. Firſt, the Stars, of which it is ſaid the aſpect to be euill, ſhould be euill by them ſelues, being made of God: or els ſhoulde become euill and miſcheuous through theic own will: of which neyther may be ſayd. The firſte maye not bee ſayde: ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that what ſoeuer thinges God made from the beginning were bery good, Geneſis <hi>1.</hi> The later may not be ſayd, for ſeeing the Starres are without life, it is not labofull to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute will bnto them: therefore as they are made in a certain high per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, ſo muſt we indge of them to be bnhurtfull. This reaſon is Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſed of Baſiſ Dom. <hi>6.</hi> and of Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe Lib. <hi>4.</hi> Derameri cap. <hi>4.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, if the beginnings of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions either honeſt or euill Doe take their originall of the Starres, or of every marmes natiuitie, there ſhall
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:6039:32"/>neede no labomakers to preſcry be what may be done, or what may be auoyded: without cauſe ſhall Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges be appointed which may honor bertue with rewardes, and puniſhe wickedneſſe with paynes. Theeues ſhal not be erccuted, others that are guiltie ſhall not be puniſhed, becauſe the conſtellation of the Stars whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they were buine, did inforce them to doe wickedly. It ſhall be ſuperfluous alſo to ereciſe Sciences to the ſuſtentation of life, ſeeing that the Starres will geue vnto vs aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of all thinges, we being idle and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rleſſe.</p>
            <p>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>uclude, The greate hope of Chriſtis is ſhall become baine, if ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ning there be a reboard nor ſinnecond aned, for becauſe that nor lang is done of men after theire will, for where as neceſſitie &amp; fate of the ſtarres haue dominition, there eſtunation for worthynes hath no
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:6039:32"/>place, which is the principal point of juſt judgement. Theſe thinges I had almoſt woide for woide out of Baſile: more migh be added to the ſame purpoſe out of other godlye wiyters.</p>
            <p>Many of the Mathematicians do ſaye that they doe not affirme the Starres to laye on neceſſity in me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s actions: but onely that they do en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clyne &amp; ſomwhat moue the mindes: and therefore as not greatlye tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting them ſelues, they are wout to bſurpe that common ſaying, that is, <hi>Sapientem poſſe dominari Aſtris,</hi> that a wyſe man may rule the Starres. By this reaſon ſurely they cudeuor to make theire cauſe more plauſible, and to bring men to agree to it.</p>
            <p>But I haue ſufficiently decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that they doe not ſo much as en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine the mindes: ſeinge that they haue not ſo much power, no not bpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> things without lyfe, that they may
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:6039:33"/>procure either frutfulnes or barran<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes. And if they did ſo much as en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline, yet ſhould many ince<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modities folovo as yet, as a litle atore I ſaid, ſpecially when there ſo fewe to be found ſo wife which can reſiſt. But ſo they ſay that afrerwar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> they may proceed further, an that they may plainly define that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fat of the ſtars are ineuitable: by which meanes ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny, whatſoeuer i ſhewed to happen prosperously or other wiſe, dare af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme, that ſo was the deſtinie: and ſo by litle and litle when you haue granited certaine thinges which to ſee too are but ſinale, ſtraightwaye they proceede, to the buylding bp of ſuch thinges by degrces as it were, which olighte by no meanes to be graunted. Wherefore it is lawfull to graunte to them neither the firſt, nor the latter: that is to ſay, neither inclination nor any neceſſitie.</p>
            <p>Therefore let vs conchide with
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:6039:33"/>Ieremie the Prophet the <hi>10.</hi> chap. that the way of the Gentiles may not be learned of vs: and the ſignes of heauen may not be feared of vs, as the Gentiles are afraid of them. for the lawes of the Gentiles are vanitie, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>The unne, the Moone, &amp; ſta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s are appointed for ſignes: and many marucilous thinges are done by them, by which men are often war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of the wil of God being juſt and good, but that they doe ſo poure in a certain hidden force into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> minds and bodies at the byrth of euerye man, that thereof come diuers ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes, as well in the whole life as in death: or that they bring to paſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thinge at all in the will and acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of men now lining, are thinges moſt vntrue, and contrary to the moide of God. The woides of C<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay the Prophet chap. <hi>47.</hi> are moſt cleare, who obiectcth in this wiſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:6039:34"/>the Babilonians, their deſire to inquire thinges to come of Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logiers. Thou art greeued, ſaith he, in the multitude of thy conceites, let the heauen gaſers, &amp; the beholders of the Starres, and them which them thinges to come by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Moone, ſtand by now and ſaue thee, &amp; ſhew what thinges ſhall come upon thee. Behold, they are become as ſtrawe, and the fire burneth them, neyther ſhall they delyuer their life from the fire &amp;. Therefore rightly is it thus determined in the firſt Colletane counſell which was helde againſte the Priſcillianiſtes about the yere of out Lorde <hi>400. In articulis Fidei, c. 21.</hi> If any man eſteeine that his Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logies or Matheſis are to be belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, let hun be accurſed. And Leo Biſhop of Roine the firſt of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name, being aſtied cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſell as touching that matter, about the yere of our Lorde <hi>450.</hi> did write backe in this maner
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:6039:34"/>to Turbius Biſh. of Aſturica: The eleuenth blaſphemie of them (hee ſpeaketh of the Priſcillianiſtes) is this where by they ſuppoſe by the fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tall Starres, both the bodies and ſoules of men to be bound: by which madnes, of neceſſitie it followeth, that they (as men wiapped in the errors of Daganes) deſire both to worſhippe the Starres fauouring them as they ſuppoſe, or to mitigate them being contrearie or diſpleaſed. but vnto ſuch as folow theſe things there is no place in the Catholic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e church, for becauſe that he that hath geuen hun ſelfe to ſuch perſwaſions is wholy gone away from the bodie of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Againe, when as yet in Spayne long after, certaine wente about to eſtabli2he thoſe falſe opinions, about the yre of our Lord <hi>630.</hi> there was appointed a Councell at Braccar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, wherein cap. <hi>19.</hi> we reade decreede:
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:6039:35"/>If any man doe belerue the ſoules and bodies of men to be bounde by fatall ſigne, as the Paganes and Priſcillians haue ſaid, let him be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurſed.</p>
            <p>And Cap. <hi>10.</hi> If any doe beleeue the twelue ſignes, that is to ſay, the ſignes which the Mathematicians are wonte to obſe rue to be ſpread a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broade thorow euery the members of the ſoule or bodie, and ſay y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> they are aſcrybed to the names of Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arches, as Priſcilianus ſaid, let him be accurſed. As therefore the ſame queſtion hath oftentimes and long bene toſſed in the Church, ſo often againe haue they condiſcended into the ſame opinion of it: whereby it may appeare, what we ſhoulde alſo thinke of it at this time.</p>
            <p>Now as touching the ſecond que<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtion, that is to ſaye, wherher any certayntie may be foreſhewed, of the lyfe and actions of men, by the
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:6039:35"/>motion and ſcituation of the Stars it is eaſie to determine. Let this be therfore eſtabliſhed, that no certayn arte of predictions or foretelliges may be ratified. The reaſon is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, as before I haue touched in the fourth reaſon, the moſt ercelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Mathematicians do not agrce a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monge themſelues of the maner of the appoyntinge of the twelue hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and of the maner of accompting: Agayne it is impoſſible eractlie to diſtingui2he thoſe ſirtieth moſt 2inale partes, into the which the degrees of the ſigns are deuided: to conclude many other things of lyke ſorte doe concurre, which witneſſe the vantric of the falſly ſuppoſed arte. They do foreſhew ſoinetyine the truthe, but (as Auguſtine ſaith <hi>libro 5. De ciuita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te Dei cap. 7.</hi>) rather beings pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap> taughte by the ſuggeſtion of ſonie euil ſpirit, then (as they ſafely ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe) leaning to the firme foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:6039:36"/>on of theire arte Whereby it cometh to paſſe, that they which are thought ſometyme to have fore ſhewed the truthe by the ayde (or warrate) of theire arte, beinge agayne deceyued verie often tymes by theire deceyue able rules, filthelie beguiled them ſelues, and alſo do beguile others. I could cecke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> infmnit examples, here of, taken out of hiſtories. Therfore euen heathen Cmperoures and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates haue ſuppoſed it to belong vnto them, to bridle ſo great a vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty by the lawes. For Ciberins, Ui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellius, Dioclccianus, Conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, Gratianus, Ualentinianus, and Theodoſius, commnaunded the Mathematicians, as hurtfull peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, to be driuen out of the city. Loke vpon Suetonius Tranquillus, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo vpon Cornelius Tacitus, Lib. <hi>2.12.18.</hi> Alſo Nicephorus Caliſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>us <hi>Hiſt. Eccleſiaſticae lib. 5. c. 24. lib. 9. ca. 5.</hi> and <hi>Lib. 11. cap. 45.</hi> And in the Ciuill
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:6039:36"/>Law they are ſeuerely puniſhed of Iuſtinian, <hi>Codue de maleficis, &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thematicis.</hi> Many alſo being cunning in Mathematical matters, haue mightely battered the whole predic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of natiuities, as Iohannes Gerſon, Iohannes Picus Miran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulanus. Therfore it is not to be maruailed at, though the holp Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers haue be ſtowed much labor in hiſſinge out, and condemning of it: Namely Epiphanius, Baſilius, Gre gorius Nazianzemis, Chryſoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, Hieronymus, Ambroſius, and Auguſtinus.</p>
            <p>Epiphanius reaſoning againſte the phariſies the <hi>16.</hi> hereſie, againſt the Maniehei hereſie <hi>66.</hi> Baſile in the ſixe dap workes, <hi>1.</hi> and <hi>6.</hi> Hom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies. Gregorius Nazianzenus in his oration of taking regard for the pooze. Alſo in his ſermon of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctians, and that it is not conuenient alwayes to reaſon of God openly.
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:6039:37"/>And in his ſeconde booke of Diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, Chryſoſtome on Grneſis, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milie <hi>5.</hi> and <hi>6.</hi> On Mathew Homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie <hi>6.</hi> where hee intreateth of the Star that appeared at the birth of Chriſt. Againe, in that worke vpon Mat. which is unperfect (the which the learned doubte whether they may father vpon Chryſoſtome.) Alſo on the Eſay, where the Prophet doeth drilie mocke, and threaten de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction to the Babilouians. who aſaed counſell at the Aſtrologiars. Amoroſe in the places vefore allea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, and of Aoraham the Partri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arche, Lib. <hi>2.</hi> Cap. <hi>3.</hi> Auguſtine of the Citie of God, Lib. <hi>5.</hi> From the beginning to the tenth Chapt. And in Lib. <hi>4.</hi> of Confeſſions, Chapter. And Lib. <hi>7.</hi> Cap. <hi>6.</hi> againſt the Aca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demians lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>7.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And of the Chriſtian doetrine lib.
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:6039:37"/>
               <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>21.22.23.24.</hi> and lib. <hi>8.</hi> of queſtions. Qu. <hi>45.</hi> in the expoſition of the <hi>31.</hi> Pſal. vpon that verſe, I will declare againſt my ſelfe mine vnrighteouſnes.</p>
            <p>And theſe thinges may ſuffiſe to the explieation of thoſe thinges which are ſet foorth by Moy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of the fourthe day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worke.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="excerpt">
            <pb facs="tcp:6039:38"/>
            <pb n="75" facs="tcp:6039:38"/>
            <head>
               <hi>WHETHER THAT THE DEVILS HAVE BENE THE</hi> Shewers of Masuall artes; and by their helpe, euill men do Woorke ſignes and wonders.</head>
            <head type="sub">Hyp. Lib. 2. pag. 306.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E reade in the <hi>7.</hi> cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Exodus, that when as Moiſes and Aaron by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement &amp; helpe of God did woorke ſignes before Pharao, to certifye, that they were by God commaunded to obtayn de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liueraunce for the people: that Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rao alſo called the wiſemen and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaunters and magicians of E gipt, which wrought y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> like ſignes, with the great admiration of all men, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſte Moyſes: and ſo were they Autors that Pharao beinge harde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, he did not obey the commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:6039:39"/>of God. And in the ſecond epiſtle to the Cheſſalonians the ſecond chapter it is ſaid, that the comm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge of that wicked man, whome the Lord ſhal dcſtroy with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> breath of his mouth, ſhalbe accordinge to the working of Satha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in all power and ſigues, and lyinge wonders, and with all deceipte of bnrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſues. By theſe and ſuch like pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces the holy Fathers haue gathered that ſigues, wounders and micacles ſomtimes be wroughte by deuiles, beſide that, that men beinge taught and helped by them, may do the like. Of which matter writ Ireueus lib. <hi>1.</hi> Cap. <hi>9.</hi> Tertullianus in manye wordes, in Apol. Cap. <hi>2.</hi> and <hi>23.</hi> Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo Auguſt. <hi>de Trinitate. Lib. 3, Cap. 7.</hi> and againe in his worke <hi>de Ciuitate Dei. lib. 8. ca, 19.</hi> where he doth wring out, euen of the Gentils themſelues this confeſſto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: to wit, that Magicall artes ought to be aſcribed as taken
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:6039:39"/>from euill ſpirites, by this meanes: for that they thought them worthy to be puniſhed by the Lawes, that exerciſe thoſe artes.</p>
            <p>I comprehende in the name of Magike, diuers artes named in the Scriptures, but which are harnie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and forbidden by God, of which there may ſeeme three orders to be appointed. In the firſt order are meautations, wilchcrafre or ingling, which doe ſpeciallie belong to delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the ſences, Of which is menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned Exod. <hi>7.</hi> Deut. <hi>18.2.</hi> Chron. <hi>33</hi> Eſay <hi>8.</hi> and <hi>47.</hi> Pſal. <hi>58.</hi> Gal. <hi>3.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2</hi> In the ſeconde order are pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced diners faſhious of ſoothſayings, or diumation, of which ſort are the obſeruation of Auguries, Deut. <hi>18.</hi> Alſo the marking of dremes, Leuit. <hi>19.</hi> Deut. <hi>13.2.</hi> Chron. <hi>32.</hi> Iere. <hi>23.</hi> and <hi>27.</hi> Zacha. <hi>10.</hi> The diuining by lottes, Deut. <hi>18.</hi> Alſo they which aſke counſaile at Spirits. Leuit. <hi>20.</hi>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:6039:40"/>Deut. <hi>18.1.</hi> Sam. <hi>28.2.</hi> Kinges <hi>21.1.</hi> Chro. <hi>10.</hi> Eſay <hi>8.</hi> and <hi>29.</hi> Act. <hi>16.</hi> Alſo they which aſke eounſell at the dead, Deut. <hi>18. 1.</hi> Sam. <hi>28.</hi> Eſay <hi>8.</hi> Luke <hi>16.</hi> By theſe founes of Diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations which the Scripture hath expreſſed, vnderſtande the reſt what ſoeuer they be, which be manifolde, as the deuill hauinge a manifolde, wiles, doth greatly reioice to put in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to mennes heades, diuers thinges that be harmefull.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3</hi> In the thirde order of Magike is numbred or accounted a certaine generall facultie of wryting diners ſignes and miracles by the helpe of euill Spirites, whereof is mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>2.</hi> Cheſ. <hi>2.</hi> But to the intente that euery man may more rightlye iudge of theſe formes of Magike, and furthermore of thoſe places of ſcripture: I will adde ſomcwhat of euery one of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Incantatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is ſaid <hi>acantando,</hi> of ſinging or chaunting,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:6039:40"/>And with the Hebrewes it is <hi>Lachat</hi> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> verbe <hi>Lachaſch,</hi> which is to whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſper, to mumble, to ſpeake with a ſtil voice, or ſoftly. Wherefore all thoſe thiuges are ſayd to be done by In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cantation or inchauntment, in which wordes, verſes, prayers, humble de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires or adiurations are vſed, nether maketh it any matter, whether be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, there are vſed inſtrumentes or obſeruations, or no. Wherby ye may note that Incantation doeth ſtretch very farre, and by the ſame very ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny and great thinges are brought to paſſe, of which ſorte are mentioned Exod. <hi>7.</hi> and ſuch as the Poets doe often ſhew. And ſo (to let paſſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) in the <hi>7.</hi> booke of the Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morph. of Ouid, a certaine wiche boaſteth her ſelfe, ſaying:
<q>
                  <l>When as I would, the bankes agaſte she riuers backs</l>
                  <l>Imo theire heades returnde: the boiſtrous ſeas likewiſe</l>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:6039:41"/>
                  <l>That rage I ſtaye, that ſtaye with Charme I make torage.</l>
                  <l>The cloudes I driue to flight, to make the ſkye looke cleare,</l>
                  <l>And bringe them in agayne when that it is my will:</l>
                  <l>Eucn ſo I vſe the windes both with my check and call.</l>
                  <l>With wordes and charmes the cruell vipers chawes I braſt.</l>
                  <l>I moue the growing rockes, and plucke from na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue ground</l>
                  <l>The mighty okes, and groues and woodes cauſe ſhake and quake.</l>
                  <l>And grounde like kine to lowe, and dead to leaue their graues.</l>
                  <l>And thee I drawe, O Moone, &amp;c.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Neither ought it to ſeeme incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſo great things are brought to paſſe by Enchauntment. For it is not to be doubted y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> there is a great force in wordes, chiefly in prayers, procceding from a faithfull harte.</p>
            <p>Wherefore as holy men do ſtay vpon the couenaute that they haue with God, and hauing made theire
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:6039:41"/>prayer, and called on the name of God they obtayne, that things not hard of, are brought to paſſe: ſo it is meet that we ſhould vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, the Magicians alſo to haue ſome coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with the Deuile. And where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as alſo they pray vnto him, call v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon him, and require his helpe, and paradue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ture with certaine cuſtoms and obſeruationes Doe as it were worſhip to him: he is at haud, and willingly doth graunt their deſires. And he doth reioyce when hee is ſo honoured and worſhiped: and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as much as he can (and hee can doe very much) he ſtudyeth to binde men vnto him, and to the intent hee may ſtill keepe them in vngodlines, he doth willingly gratifie them: and although otherwhile in ſuch kind of prayers there ſeeme to be mingled certaine wordes that be gooly, reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious, and ſomewhatagreeing with lawfull inuocation of God, yet ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:6039:42"/>is alway found either in the words themſelues, or els in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rites and circumſtances, or els in the cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes mouing, or in the effects follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that tendeth to the reproche of God, and where with God is temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, blaſphemed, mocked, deſpiſed, and therefore the deuill reioyceth, turneth all thinges to his owne ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and readilie doeth perfourme thoſe thinges which he ſeeth to be aſked of him. Let euery prayer be ſuſpected, which ſwarueth, yea but a little, from that ſimple faſhion of praying, the which the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures doe ſhew. Oftentimes, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as a more gay kinde of Religion (to ſee to) is brought in, there the greter ſinne lurketh. God hath forbidden to abuſe at any time, his holy name, Euery falſe imitation of Religion is a poyſon of true Religion. In ſum, Incantation doth ſignifie a meane, whereby men doe require helpe of
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:6039:42"/>the deuill, and whereby he is moued to ſuceoure, or to ſet forwarde their appointed inchauntmentes or<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing lines.</p>
            <p>Furthermore, bewithinges, and inglinges with the Hebrues, cal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led <hi>Chaſchias,</hi> in latine called <hi>Fuſcinato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, &amp; Praeſtigatores.</hi> (which words are Erod. 7. Miche. 5. and Galat. 3) are vnderſtanded, by the conſente of all Interpreters, t be done when the ſences of men are ſo hurte and illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that they all think, that certain vnwonted thinges are broughte to paſſe, or els naturall thinges are chaunged. And therefore with the wordes of bewitchinge or iuglinge, propertic is noted the formall cauſe, and the meane, whereby the deuill will ſatiſfie the deſires of men: or els, when as otherwiſe he is a lyar, and a deceauer, hee fayneth at the leaſt wiſe, that he doth ſatiſfic. And if we look more narrowly, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> nature
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:6039:43"/>of Relatiues is after a ſorte ſeene in Incantations and bewitchinges, while they (that is, inca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tations) are vnderſtanded to be wroughtby men that requeſt ſomewhat to be done, and theſe (that is, bewitchinges) are vnderſtanded to be wrought by the deuill, willinge to perfourme thoſe thinges which are requeſted. And they properly vnto whom the deuill hath ſhewed by this meane, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> way to bringe to paſſe anye vnwonted thinges, are ſayde, to bewitche, and to iuggle to the decreauinge of the minds and ſences of men. Therfore of this ſorte is that which is read in the life of S. Macarius. Certaine Parentes ſuppoſed-their daughter to be turned into a Cowe, becauſe that their ſences were ſo hurte by the bewitching of the deuill, or ſome ill perſons, that they did ſee no other thing in their daughter, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhape and all the actions of a Cowe, and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:6039:43"/>they thought plainly that ſhe was a Cowe. But Macharius, when they came to him with the ſuppoſed Cowe, ſaw a very wenche, rightly arrayed with all ſuch apparraue as became a woman: becauſe forſooth, he could not be hurte with bewith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the deuill having no power vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, But when as hee had fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uently called vpon God, all the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witching alſo was taken away from the Parents, and ſtraightway they knew their daughter, ſuch as before they did. Neither was her ſhape of a wenche taken away from her, but onely the ſeuces of the beholders were deluded, that they thought it to be taken away.</p>
            <p>So alſo doth Auguſtine, <hi>De Ciuit. Dei, Lib. 18. cap. 17. &amp; 18.</hi> ſuppoſe the mates of Uliſſes to be chaunged in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to diuers beaſtes: and in Archadia, that men while they did ſwimme o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer a ſtagne or poole, were turned
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:6039:44"/>into wolues. De addeth alſo that in his time, certaine in Italic, when they had caten cheeſe, were turned into Aſſes, and the ſame, althoughe alwayes they remayned ſounde in reaſon, to haue caried lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gtune great burthens, and after that to be tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to their former ſhape. Neither ſurely do the deuils (ſaith he ca. <hi>18.</hi>) create natures if they doe anye of thoſe thinges whereof in this que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion is diſcourſed: but chaunge in ſhape onely, thoſe thinges which are created of the true God, that they ſeeme to be that which they bee not, and therefore I beleue that not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the minde, but alſo that the bodie neither, can by any reaſon, by arte or power of deuils, be truely altered in to the members or lineamentes of beaſtes.</p>
            <p>Thus ſayeth Auguſtine. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore of theſe things is manifeſt, that bewitchinge doth ſtretch very farre
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:6039:44"/>and that vnder it are comprehended all thinges, which are don with the eluſion of the ſenſes: that thinges are beleued to be ſene, harde, and perceyued, which notwithſtandinge are no ſuch maner of thinges. And it is no hard matter for the deuill, or his diſciples beinge ſtudious of magike, to do theſe thinges. For the ſenſes of men are by diuers meanes deceyued. Firſt, when that ſome fraude or chaunge is commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in that thinge which is laide be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ſenſes. By which reaſone the deuill taketh to him, and againe putteth from him, ſuche bodies or ſhapes as pleſeth him: by the ſame reaſon he can ſhewe foorth all kinde of bodies and ſhapes, and put forth the ſame to the ſenſes, to be ſene and touched and by ſome meanes or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be perceyued. S. Hierome in the lyfe of Hilarion doth ſhewe, that the deuill did ſomtune ſet forth
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:6039:45"/>before the ſaide holy man to be hard of him the cryinge of yong children, the wailing and lamentation of wo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>men, the noyſe of armies, the bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of cattell, and ſtraunge ſounds of diuers voyces, that he ranne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way rather for the ſounde than for the ſight. And a while after he ſhew<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth: at vnawares, when the Mone ſhined, he ſawe a chariot with fiery horſes to runne vpon him: and whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he had caled vpon Ieſus, before his eyes all the pompe was ſwalowed vp with a ſodden openinge of the earth. He addeth: how ofre naked women appered vnto him while he laye, how ofte verie great ple<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ie of delicates appered to him beinge an hungred. And he reckeneth vp cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine other thinges. And all things were on this wiſe prepared of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiles, which to call hym away from faith, from feruent inuocation, and contemplation of deuine things, did
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:6039:45"/>ſet forth things not true, but ſhapes and unages of thinges, or els bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies for the time formed. Secondly the inſtrumentes of the ſenſes, or y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meanes by which they worke, are otherwhi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſtriken &amp; hurt, by reaſon whereof they cannot decerner. As for erample: many tymes ſuch hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors are ſhed aboute the eyes, for the which ſome man beleueth that he loketh thorowe a ſyue, that he ſeeth gnattes or other ſinal bodies, parthy cleare, partly unſtie, alſo cob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>webbes, the ſmal heyres of wol, circles about candels, that are ligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>che diſeaſe the Phiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians call (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) <hi>ſuffuſio,</hi> a ſheading abrode, or a web, in the eye: and in ertendinge ſhe ſight of the eye, all bodiesſeme leſſe, but in diminiſhing thereof, they all ſeme greater. They that are ſioke of of the diſeaſe called Glaucoma, (which is a humor in the eyes like chriſtall) accordinge to
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:6039:46"/>the proportion of the humor aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge, do thinke all thinges are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſly colowred. And how the ſight and other ſenſes of them that be dronken are deceyued for becauſe of the groſſe humors that are diſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, is too much knowne. And how ſaye you by this that the Media or meanes which are put in betwene the inſtrument of the ſighte and the bodies laid againſt it, do often bring to paſſe, that thinges are iudged to be other the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they be. Through glaſſe the ſenſe and color is chaunged: the ſame may likewiſe happen of ſubtile or thinne humors and exhalations diſperſed by the ayre nigh vnto vs. And wood that is parte put into the water, appeareth croked, the which notwithſtanding is right. For that, that thinges put betweene the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments of the ſences, and the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies layde againſt them, doe cauſe ſuch deceauing ſhapes. And theſe
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:6039:46"/>impedimentes can the deuill eaſilye bring forth, as well in the inſtrume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the ſight, as in the inſtruments of the other ſences: and he doth ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guile men, that they beleue and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue other things then in deed they ſee and perceaue.</p>
            <p>Thirdlye, manie times are the powers of the mind troubled, I ſay memorie, vnderſtandinge or reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, thought, imagination, and the reſt that are toyned to them, wherof it commeth, that they which are ſo affected, ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not any more iudge right and they thinke they heare, ſee, and perceaue wondrous things, and yet they are deceaued. Theſe effectes are ſeene in them which are ſicke of the phrenſie, melancholie, or mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. Galene in his booke of the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences of the effectes that followe ſickneſſes, doth ſhew that Theophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus the phiſition when he was ſicke of the phrenſie, be thought that hee
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:6039:47"/>ſaw and hearde miuſirels continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally playing in his chamber, and he commaunded they ſhould be dryuen out. But when he was recouered, he could tell of all thinges, that he, or they which came to him, ſayd or did: that is to ſay, becauſe only imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in him was hurte, and not cogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation or reaſoning. In many that are phrenſie, reaſoning or cogitation is onely hurte, in ſome the memorie alſo, and more powers of the minde.</p>
            <p>Furthermore, the molancholicall humor hauing dommion, doth cauſe that ſome doe thinke themſelues to be bruite beaſtes, whoſe voyces and motions they imitate: that they be ſtone or glaſſe veſſell: that they are inuaded of murtherers &amp; enemies: that they are inſpyred with the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of God, and foreſhew things to come.</p>
            <p>Hotte humors, as bloude and ye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low choler, when they abounde, and
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:6039:47"/>doe moleſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> brayn, they cauſe mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and woodneſſe, ſo that men vſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues after the manner of wilde beaſts. And who is ignorante, that the imagination of ſome otherwhile is ſo vehement, either when they wake, or when the other ſences are at reſt through ſlepe, that they think themſelues to perceaue &amp; doe thoſe thinges, which notwitſtanding, by no meanes they doe? Wheras ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore deuils, when God doth permit, can infecte meate, drinke, the ayre that is diſperſed about vs, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore alſo may ſtrike our bodies with diſeaſes and other diſcommodities, it is neuer a whit to be maruayled at, if alſo they hurte our brayne and the powers of the minde abydinge therein, that we thinke we doe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue, and doe ſtraunge thinges.</p>
            <p>Hether may be referred that which Auguſtine in the <hi>18.</hi> booke <hi>De Ciuit. Dei cap. 18.</hi> doth make mention of, in
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:6039:48"/>theſe wordes: A certaine man did reporte that at his owne houſe, in the might, before hee ſlept, he ſaw a certaine Philoſopher very well kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen vnto him, comming vnto him, and that he did expounde vnto him certaine Platonicall matters, which he being afore requeſted, would not open. And when it was demaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of the ſame philoſopher why he did that in that other mans houſe which he denyed to doe in his owne houſe when he requeſted it? I did it not, ſaide he, but I dreamed that I did it. But by this meanes, that which the one dreamed, was decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vnto the other being awake, by a phantaſticall Image. Thus much hath Auguſtine.</p>
            <p>And a little before in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame place he had ſayd, The fantaſie of man, as in dreaming when men ſleepe, ſo alſo in cogitation, while they wake, may be innumerable kinds or ſorts
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:6039:48"/>of things be diuerſly altered: of this ſorte is that, which in a certain Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non of the Auciran counſell, held the yeare <hi>308.</hi> Certaine doe affirme to be written: &amp; it is reported of Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian <hi>26.</hi> Dueſt. <hi>5.</hi> Canon. Epiſcopi. Certayne wicked women beynge gone backe after Sathan, ſeduced by illuſions of deuils and phanfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, do beleue and porfeſſe that they do ryde vpon certaine beaſtes in the nighte houres, with Diana a god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the pagans, or with Hero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dias, or with an innumerable mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of women, and that they paſſe ouer a great deale of grounde in the dead time of the night, and that they obay her commaundement as their Lady miſtres and that they are cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine nights called foorth to doe her ſeruice.</p>
            <p>And after a few wordes he ſaith: Prieſtes ought to preach, that by all meanes theſe thinges are falſe, and
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:6039:49"/>that ſuche phanteſies are put into the mindes of the faythfull not by a godly ſpirite, but by a wicked ſpirit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> for Sathan which doth tranſfigure or chaunge him ſelfe into an aungell of lighte, when he hath faken the minde of any woman, and hath ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued her vnto him through vnbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leefe, ſtraightway doth tranſforme himſelfe into diuers faſhions, and ſimilitudes of diuers perſons, and doth bring out of the way by all by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes, the minde which he holdeth captitle, deluding it in dreames, ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing ſomewhile ioyful things, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>while heauie thinges, ſomewhile knowen perſons, ſomewhile vnkno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen perſons. And when as only the ſpirite doth ſuffer this, the vnfaith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full minde ſuppoſeth theſe things to happe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not in the ſoule, but in the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die &amp;c. Theſe and ſuch like thinges therefore happen when as the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of the minde (as I ſayd before)
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:6039:49"/>are troubled.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, The deuils oftentimes doe quicklye place ſome bodies in ſteade of other ſome: whereof it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to paſſe, that we ſuppoſe thoſe former to be chaunged into the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and ſo our ſences are deceaued by the only alteration of the bodies. And therfore Auguſt. in his worke <hi>De Ciuitate Dei. Lib. 18. Cap. 18.</hi> doeth ſay: That the felowes af Diome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des were not chaunged into birdes (as they commonlye fabled) but that they were taken away and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed by euill Aungels, Reuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, and in their ſtead Birdes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing brought from ſome other place, were ſodainly ſet downe: the which birdes thoſe that haue falſly ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed thoſe men to be turned into ſince that time haue called the fellowes of Diomedes, or Diomedes hys birdes. In like maner Iphigenia y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> daughter of Agamemnon, when ſhe
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:6039:50"/>ſtoode before the aulter to be ſlaine, was quickly taken away by ſome euill Spirite, and in her place was placed an hind, the ſame ſpirit doing it. This is a token that it is true, for that ſhe was afterwarde found aliue in Cherſoneſus beſide y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne Taurus, And there was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidenſe of Dianas ſacrifice. And oftentimes are vnbeleuers by this meanes deceyued of deuiles, and theſe mockages haue geuen a begin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ning to ſo many triflinge tranſfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations, as of Ouid and other are famouſly ſet forth.</p>
            <p>From theſe doth not greatly dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the fraud of certaine vacabunds iugglers, which playing with the nimbleneſſe of theire arms &amp; hands are thoughte to thruſte themſelues thoro we the arme, or tongue or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> with a dagger, to drawe out bloud, and to do many other things, when as notwithſtandinge they do
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:6039:50"/>nothinge els but ſodenly chaung the inſtruments, and doe deceyue with the onely ſwiftnes of motions. By theſe meanes therefore &amp; by others which the deuile being endued with the knowledge of natureall thinges, and with paſſinge experience, doth vnderſtand, and mans wit doth not conceyue: men may be deceyued, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well of the deuill him ſelfe, as of thoſe whome he teacheth, ſo that of diuers things they apprehend falſe opinions. And God doth ſomtime permitte, that eyther with incanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or els with the foreſaide forms of illuſions, men be hurt or take da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, whether in theire bodies or in ſences of the minde, or in o? ther thinges, not for becauſe of the vertue or ſtrength of any wordes or actions, which are done of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitians with obſeruatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as though in them were ſome ſyngular force: but for the couenante that priuelie
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:6039:51"/>they haue with the deufles, by cen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſone of which couenant the deuiles do gladly performe onto there wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipperes the things which they te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, as farre as they can, and ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially thoſe things which are fitte to hurt. Moreouer God doth permitte. the deuiles to exerciſe theire power upon ſome, as well for the ſinnes of them which deſire that other may be hurt: the which becauſe they haue once geuen them ſelues to the deuil, God will harden in theire wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes: as alſo for theire ſinnes who are touched with the harme, or els for ſome other cauſes whcih are hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, and yet alwayes on God his behalfiuſt. According to which opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion I haue read Augnſtin in a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine palce to haue ſpoken as tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinge theſe matters. Neither ſures; iy it is lawfull to put away theſe miſchicfes with other miſchiefes, that is to ſaye, with charmes or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bocaffon
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:6039:51"/>of deuilles: for that were to aſke at the deuill, the author of all euile, that which is good, which ought to be waighted for at God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, and of him is wonte to be ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen: but by faith in God, and the fruites of faith, that is to ſay with prayer and almes, we muſt require of God that he accordinge to his goodnes deliuer vs from eilill. And if it be not ſo taken awaye, then if remaineth that we ſuffer paffenflie all incommodities, as longe as it ſhall ſeeme good to him to puniſhe and to trie vs, Which maner of cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel againſt this kind of temptations and daungers to be bſed is here &amp; there commended in the ſoripfures, alſo in the 33 queſtion, 1 Cano. <hi>Spiper Sortiarias.</hi> And ſo alſo Macaruis brought to paſſe, that the parentes of the wench were no longer letted with the bewitehing &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Now muſt I ſpeake of thoſe things
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:6039:52"/>which I haue referred to the ſecond order of magicall matters, that is to ſay of diuinations. I haue reeke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vp thoſe formes of diuinations, which the ſcripture doth mention, if anie deſire more, he may ſeeke them out of other wrytcrs. In the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes writhinges they are all in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall condenmed: And the godlie are commaunded to aunyde them: and that chiefly for theſe cauſes.</p>
            <p>firſt for that they are inuented of the deuill, whoſe workes are all euile, and do tend alwaye vnto miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe. Wherfore very farre are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, prophane diuination, and holy propheſie: aſ well becauſe that is faught of an euil ſpirite, and this is adininiſtred of God and the holie Ghoſt: as alſo becauſe that is not of what things ſo euer, but onely of certayne thinges and for the moſt part euill? and this may be accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of what things ſoeuer, but eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redye
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:6039:52"/>ſee the naturall cauſes pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared. For naturall cauſes beinge layde, the effecfes doe alwayes (for the moſt parte) follow. By which teaſon both Phiſitions and Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandmen ofcen doe fore ſee that cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine thinges do follow of ſure cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. And in bruite beaſtes alſo may be conſidered in certaine hidden po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of perceauing afore things that are to come: whereof are noted by their motions and actions raine, te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſtes and many ſuch like thinges. And becauſe they are throughly cun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ning in many thinges by long erpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience of time, they can moſt certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pronounce of aſ ſuch like thinges. Therefore oftentimes doe they ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Propheſies of thoſe effectes which are wrought by the helpe of naturall thinges.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, they doe marke what
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:6039:53"/>thinges are alreadie prepated in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny place or beginne to be done. And theſe ſelfe ſame things then ſtraight way ſhew to ſome bodie (dwelling) in another place, and perhappes far diſtante, which as a Prophet doeth manifeſt the ſame to all men, and de ſireth to ſeeme to bee a ſhewer of thinges to come. And when y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> men of that place, do after a certain ſpace perceaue that the matter is ſo as it was tolde them, they thinke that of that thinge there was bttered a pro pheſie. Yea eaſie it is for the deuil, which is of a moſt ſubtile and moſt nimber nature, and doth moſt ſwift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pearce into euery place, to ſpy out whatſoeuer thinges are done on eue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry ſide, and of the ſame to bringe ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinges whether he liſteth. But they doe not perceiue the thoughtes od men (the which Auguſtine graun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth that he ſome while thought, but he did afterwarde determine other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:6039:53"/>in his ſeconde booke of Retra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctations, Cap. <hi>30.</hi>) but they note the ſignes onely, and the wordes and ſpeaches and the geſhires of the bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dies, where with the thoughts of the minde are after a ſorte ſet forth: and by theſe and other thinges concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring they iudge as certainly as they can. fourthly, they ſhew things to come, which in ſome place or other they haue vnderſtoode to be for ſhew<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed of an holy Prophet, or ſome good Aungell: which notwitſtanding is not publiſhed among others. And ſo that which is other folkes, they doe ſuttlely challenge and ſhew out for their owne, and doe hunt for the prayſe and glorie for themſelues.</p>
            <p>fiftly, they dare oftentimes fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhew things to come, although they haue no certainfie, and are fouly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued, after which forte ſometime certaine lightbrained felowes dare affirme as thinges moſte certaine,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:6039:54"/>theſe thinges which by coniectures they doe gather as wel as they can. And that doe the deuils, as well when any impedimentes may be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaged, to which it ſhalve imputed, that the ſucceſſe hath not anſwered: as alſo when willingly they are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous to deceaue; &amp; to deſtroy thoſe of whome they are aſked counſell. Hether belong theſe doutfull Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles geuen in Delphos, and in other places, as bnto Creſus: <hi>Creſus perdet Halym tranſgreſſus plurima regna.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>oke for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> her of, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the ende <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> And vnto Pirrhus: <hi>Aio te Aeacida Romanos vmcers poſſe.</hi> The which they would not vſe if as ofte as they would, they coulde ſhew the truty. And of theſe maner. of doings you may ſee many things in Auguſtine in his booke <hi>De diuina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione Daemonum. cap. 5.</hi> whcih alſo ars repeated <hi>26.</hi> queſt. <hi>3.</hi> &amp; <hi>4.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hereof may we gather what may be ſpoken of the old prophets of the Centils, and of them which while
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:6039:54"/>they were aſked counſel as touching doubtfull matters and thinges to come, did geue Oracles or anſwers. The fatetelling Prophetiſſe in Del<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phos was inſpired and gaue aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſweres, either with a ſtill winde, or by fire which brake out of the den, or els ſitting in the ſecrete ſanctuary vpon a braſen ſeate which hauinge three or foure feete, was dedicated vnto the God. So the Prophet in Branchis did ſit vpon an Areltree, orels did carie in his hande a rodde which was geuen him of ſome god: ſometime hee did waſhe his feete with water. Among the Ligurians in Thracia the prieſtes of Bacchus did drinke wine ſuſtely.</p>
            <p>Of theſe therefore and ſuch like we muſt ſay, that the rite and ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitous ceremonie being put to, ma keth nothing to the purpoſe, &amp; that it is only a ſigne of the obſeruaunce and wuenant of wicked perſons and
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:6039:55"/>euill ſpirites betwene them ſelues: and the ſpirites ſo to the honoured, and ſo retaine men in a foliſh per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion. As touching the anſwers themſelues or the inſpiration, what ſoener concerneth this cometh from the deuil, who doth teach it priuilie or apertly, to wit, with ſome repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentaſtons which he ſheweth forth, with ſightes or hiſſings, whcih voice or other ſignes. But ſaith ſome, what ſhall we determine of the Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>billes? there is no doubte but they were taught thoſe thinges, which they did foretell rightly and trulie, eſpecially of Chriſt, and things per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyning to the ſaluation of mankind by the mſpiration of the holy Ghoſt, neſſher onght it to ſeeme ſtraunge that I ſhould ſo ſay of gentlles and vnbelee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ers, when as it is appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant that the holy Ghoſt ſometime hath ſpoken true and notable things of Chriſt, euen by the wicked: as by
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:6039:55"/>Baleam Num. <hi>24.</hi> and by Caia. Io. <hi>11.</hi> Although manie thinges wece <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> obſcurely ſpoken by them thau it may be doubted, whether they v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> deeſſode thoſe thinges which they ſaſde: as neither Caia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>has did pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly vnderſtand his propheſie. But it pleaſed God that ſuch propheſies ſhould be manifeſted ſo the Gent vs to thend that afeereard, if at ante tyme they did ſirnie agaunſt Chriſt and the truth beinge manifeſieu in the carth, they might be conainced by theire owne mens predicftions &amp; teſtunomes. Cn which end to be v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, they ought alſo to haue great waigh or importance as Angaſim in his oration againſt the Iemes and Pagans cap. <hi>16.</hi> and agauiſt I. Manich. lib. <hi>13.</hi> cap. <hi>25.</hi> Chriſoſt. <hi>homilia 3 in epiſtolam ad Titum,</hi> do wit neſſe. And the inoſte auncient wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters conterding againſt the Gennls for our religion, haue willingly for
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:6039:56"/>that cauſe vſed the teſtimonfe of the Sivilles as Iuſtinus Martir, Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens Alerandrinus, Lactantius Firmianus S. Auguſtin and other. Hitherto as touchinge dininations, auſwers, and predictions.</p>
            <p>Nowe the matter requireth that I ſhould ſpeake ſomwhat of miracles, which I haue put in the third order amonge magicall matters, Do the end that euery man may more eaſily marke, what maner of miracles, and how miracles may be done of the deuill and his diſciples beinge experte in magike, it ſhall auaile to ſhew which are true miracles. Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racls properlie are ſaide to be cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine outward works or deeds had in admiration among memand ſuch in deed as appeare to be wroughte by Gods power for to declare the truth and certaintie of doctrine, of faith, or of God his promiſſes, or els y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> power of God, &amp; to the glory of
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:6039:56"/>God. This definition is gathered of cauſes, and by it may be vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded how the miracles of Chriſt and holy men may be diſtinguiſhed from theſe which are wroughte either of the deuill or of wicked men: which alſo ought to be called, not true but lying miracles, as the Apoſtle ſaith <hi>2</hi> Cheſſa. <hi>2.</hi> And theſe lying ſignes or miracls may diuerſly be wrought by the wicked.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1</hi> Firſtly, miracls are done in thoſe things in which the things are in deed ſuch, as they apeare to be: after which forte the Magitians of Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rao are beleued to haue broughte forthe ſerpentes in deed and other things of that forte: but thoſe are two wayes done. The Firſt by cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling on the name of God, as Chriſt ſpeeketh of the falſe Prophts Mat. <hi>7.</hi> that in the laſt day they ſhall ſay: Lord haue not we caſt out deuills in thy name? notwithſtandinge it
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:6039:57"/>ſhall be ſaid to them, I know you not. After the ſame maner Chriſt doth foreſhew Mat. <hi>24.</hi> falſe chriſts and falſe prophets to worke ſignes and wonders, and miracls are done ſo by them, not becauſe God is mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued with theire faith and holynes (which vtterly is none) but for the inuocation of his name which they vſe vnto him: moreouer for the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ſtanding by, whom God will haue either confirmed in found dor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trme by miracles, or els doth ſuffer them to be caried awaye ſtom the ſame. And the wicked doe vſe the name of God in theſe inuocations, but not rightly, neither to lawfull ends: wherefore more rightly they do abuſe it, which alſo ſhall happen to them to thewe damnation: of which matter Chriſoſt. hath ſpoken ſomwhat tom. <hi>5</hi> Homil. <hi>21.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3</hi> The ſecond by callinge vpon the deuil: for the Magitians with their
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:6039:57"/>charmes do call vpon enell ſpirites and allure them, the which alſo for the couenaunt that is betwen them, are ready to do any thing. And God doth geue them leaue, ſo that they ran faſhion certain bodies for a time which with our ſenſes are percea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, as I haue aforeſaid. And by this meanes did Pharao his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicians worke miracles: of whoſe whiſperinges, that is to ſay, ſtill in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocationes the ſcripture ſpeaketh plainely Exod. <hi>7.</hi> &amp;c. Although in theſe ſigns or wonders very things are laied before the ſenſes, yet ſhall they not be called true miracles: ſith that the other cauſes which muſt be conſidered in true and properly ſaid nuracles, are lackinge.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2</hi> Secondly, miraels are wrought of ſpirites and euill men, in which veric things are done and ſene, but vſing certaine natural things onely. For in ſtones, hearvs, and ſuch like
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:6039:58"/>thinges there is a certayre hidden force or ſtregth, wherwith ſtraunge things may be done, and the deuns and magitians haue notable know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of ſuch naturall forces, others in the meaue while, which do not vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d this vſe of natural things doe ſuppoſe greate miracles to be wrought, when there is nothinge leſſe. Such a thinge is it that the lampe which neuer goeth out in a certaine chappell of Venus is coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a miracle: when as notwithſian ding that may be done by arte and naturall inſtruments, that is to ſay with the ſtone called Aſpheſtus, which is found in Arcadia: (as ſaith Plini. lib. <hi>37.</hi> cap. <hi>10</hi>) and is of that uature, that beinge once kindled it neuer goeth out. And Plini. maketh mention in the <hi>18</hi> boke of his natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral hiſtory. Chap. <hi>1.</hi> of Limis viuus or aſpheſtinue (a kind of flar) that it can not be conſumed by fire. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:6039:58"/>theſe miracls alſo becauſe they are not done by the power of God but rather by a naturall force, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue not to be reckoned among true racles.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3</hi> Thirdly, miracles are done by magitians, in which certaine things appeare to the ſenſes, and yet are not verie things: but there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing els, but that the ſenſes of men are deceaued and deluded, that they thinke they ſee and perceaue things which neuertheles they neither ſet nor perceaue. Which deceate, how many ways it may be done, I haue afore declared. Therefore not theſe neither ought to be deemed true mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles, becauſe the very things are wanting, and the ſenſes are decea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4</hi> Fourthely. By what meanes ſoeuer, eyther apart or priuie, mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles are wrought by Magicians, and whether verie thinges be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayning
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:6039:59"/>in them, or onely do falſly appence: yet aſlonge as the cauſes, once manbred in the definition, are not ſene in ſhem, they can not be indged any other but lyenge ſignes and lyenge unra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>es. For they can not be true, which art neither done by the true power of God, neither to the preſor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ed ends, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, to pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the truth of doctrine, of faith, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of Gods proiniſſes, or of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ght of God, nor are directed to ſet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>th the glory of God. Neuertheles <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> vuto the wicked is gran<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> to worke miracles, ſuch as the Godly can not: as Chriſt hath ſignified Mat. <hi>24.</hi> ſainge: that f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſe prophetes and falſe chriſtes ſhould worke ſignes and wouderes: that euen the electe, if it might be, may be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>aued. And yet not therefore as rightly Auguſtine doth note lib. <hi>83. queſtionum queſti. 79,</hi> are the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked to be thoughtmore worthy then
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:6039:59"/>the godly, or more acceptable vnto God, as neither the Magicians be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Phar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> more hette<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Moy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes the man of God: Although the wicked h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e not power geuen them to worke miracles where and when they wall: but onely where, when, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> how it ſeemeth good to God. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore theſe Magicians of Egypt, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they the need ſerpents, blon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>aters and frogs, which were an deede great matices: Yet when they came to lice, they could doe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing: and they were compelled to to confeſſe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Moyſes did all things with the finger of God, that is to ſay, by Gods power, Good.s. Alſo the Grorciſtes Act. <hi>19.</hi> are not able to drine out the euill ſpirite. So al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes at the length muſt a lie geue place to the trueth. There are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners cauſes for which God doth geue ſo great power to the vngodly</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1</hi> The firſt: If any of the vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:6039:60"/>doe worke miracles, vſing inuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the name of God: the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> muſt we vnderſtand thoſe miracles to be brought to paſſe for the onely wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſſe of the name of God: for that God wil haue his name to be had in beneration, neither doth he ſuffer it in vayne to be called vpon: of which matter I haue touched ſomewhat afore.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2</hi> The ſecond cauſe, If any work miracles, not calling vpon the name of God, but by other meanes, as by helpe of deuils, &amp;c. This hapneth that the euill, that is to ſay, as well they that worke the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as thoſe which looke on them and follow them, ane confirmed in euill, are ſeduced and drawen into new erxours. After which ſorte Pharao and the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians were hardened in euill. And <hi>2.</hi> Theſſ. <hi>2.</hi> the wicked are blineded that they ſhould beleeue lyes.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3</hi> The third cauſe: Vnto the wic<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ked
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:6039:60"/>power to doe miracles is geuen, that the conſtancie of the godly may be tryed, and their patience exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. Whereof it is ſayd Deut. <hi>13.</hi> that God, by a falſe Prophet which foreſheweth true things, &amp; worketh miracles, doth trie his people. Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Magus is written to haue wrought many wonders againſte Peter the Apoſtle.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4</hi> The fourth cauſe: Euil me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are ſuſſered to worke miracles, leaſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly men (vnto whom the ſame facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie is by God grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted) ſhould be too proude in them ſelues, and ſhoulde hunte after vaine glorie: Moreouer leaſt the reſidue of men ſhould mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure holineſſe by miracles: Or els, which is greater, and ſoundeth to Gods diſhonoure, that they ſhoulde giue godly worſhippe vnto them, as Act. <hi>15.</hi> the men of Licaonia, for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of a lame ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reſtored to helth, would by and by giue diuine honors
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:6039:61"/>and ſacrifices to Paule and Barna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bas.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <hi>5</hi> The fifte cauſE: that happeneth leſt any ſhould thinke the gifte of working miracles to be greatly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>red, before manie other giftes, which aſwell are more neceſſarie to the church of God, as alſo do oringe more plentifull profit: of which ſorte ſpecially are the giftes of propheſie, go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>enment &amp;c. For God doth, gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh his church at all ſeaſones with ſo ſorie giftes, the which good doe v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e to manie good purpoſes: and ſome gifts in the meane while are ſomtime common to the vugodlie, but they fowly abuſe them: therfore as manie vugodly me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doe ſometime abuſe the gifte of tongues, of wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, or the like, euen ſo doe they ſomewhile abuſe the gift of miracls Therefore as the Apoſtle geueth warning. <hi>1.</hi> Corinth, <hi>11.</hi> let vs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold and embrace the more excele<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:6039:61"/>giftes. Hether beiongeth that alſo, that Chriſt ſaith to his diſcipls Luc. <hi>10.</hi> re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oce not in this that ſpirits are ſubiecte vnto you: but reioyce be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe your names are written in heauen.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <hi>6</hi> The ſixt cauſe: Therefore alſo ſignes and wonders are wrought<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of vngodly and falſe feachers, ſeſt raſhly we ſhould receaue any dor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, which ſhall happen to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by miracles: or rather that we require not the doctrine which is ſet forth to vs to be eſtabliſhed with ſignes and wonders. Both doe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like incurre reprehenſion, (that is,) caſilie to beleue for becauſe of mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, and not to beleue ercept unra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles be adiovned. The former is a ſigne of light headed men: the later, of vnbeleeuers. Of the former it is plainly ſayd Deu. <hi>13.</hi> If there ariſe in the midſt of thee a Prophet, or a Dreamer of dreames, and geue thee
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:6039:62"/>a ſigne or a wonder, and that ſigne or wouder which he hath foretolde thee come to paſſe: and he ſhall ſay, let vs goe after ſtrange gods which thou haſt not knowen, &amp; let vs ſerue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: thou ſhalt not heare the words of that Prophet, or him which hath dreamed ſuch maner of dreame. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Lord your God doth te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pte you, that he may know whether ye loue the Lorde your God with all your harte, and with all your ſoule. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e ſhall walke after the Lord your God, and him ſhall ye feare: ye ſhall keepe his commaundementes, and heare his voice: ye ſhall ſerue him, and claue vnto him.</p>
            <p>Of the latter, that is to ſay, that we uſhold not require ſignes for co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of the doctrine, is ertante the greeuous chiding of Chriſt to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewes, Mat. <hi>12.</hi> The wicked and adulterous generation ſeek a ſigne; but no ſigne ſhall be geuen them, but
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:6039:62"/>the ſigne of Ionas the prophet. And <hi>1.</hi> Cor. <hi>1.</hi> the Iewes reqire a ſigne, and the Greekes wiſdome. It re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayneth then that indgement tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching doctrine which is ſet foor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h, muſt not be taken of miracles ioynd therto, but of the word of God, that is, the writinges of the Prophetes and Apoſtles, as Chriſt doeth diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſſe Luke <hi>16.</hi> where he bringeth in Abraham ſpeakinge: They haue (ſaith he) Moyſes &amp; the Prophets, let them heare them. And if they heare not Moyſes &amp; the Prophets neither will they beleeue if any riſe againe from the dead. And Eſaia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as ſaith cap. <hi>8.</hi> Aſke counſell at your charming Diuines which mumble and ſay: Doth not a people aſke counſell at his goddes? Shal men runne to the dead for the liuinge? Get thee to the law and Te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie.</p>
            <p>Therefore let vs know that all
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:6039:63"/>doctrine which agreeth not with the holy Scripture, is to be reie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ted although great miracles are ioynd, and though Paule himſelfe, or an Angell from heauen, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirme the ſame. Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lath. <hi>1.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <closer>Soli Deo honor &amp; gloria.</closer>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="translated_phrases">
            <p>
               <hi>The Engliſh of thoſe Latine verſes not Engliſhed, Pag. 92.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>1 Croeſus</hi> paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing <hi>ouer Halys</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Shall deſtroy many kingdomes,</hi> meaning other mens.<note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>he ambigu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>e beeing in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> word <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                              <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>t</hi> which ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>ieth both to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>troy &amp; loſe.</note>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Shall looſe many kingdomes,</hi> meaning his owne.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2</hi> I ſay O Pyrthus thou mayſt ouercome the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Or<note place="margin">For it hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oth there ſen <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>in the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e &amp; it is to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> conſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ued <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="6 letters">
                        <desc>••••••</desc>
                     </gap>way you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note>
               </item>
               <item>I ſay O Pyrthus the Romanes may ouer come thee.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
